<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The almost Christian discovered, in some sermons on Acts 26, 28 with a blow at profaneness / by the R.R. Ezekiel Hopkins, late Lord Bishop of London-Derry ; to which is added the upright Christian discovered, gathered out of the judicious treatises of William Bates, D.D.</title>
            <author>Hopkins, Ezekiel, 1634-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11835934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11835934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 497:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The almost Christian discovered, in some sermons on Acts 26, 28 with a blow at profaneness / by the R.R. Ezekiel Hopkins, late Lord Bishop of London-Derry ; to which is added the upright Christian discovered, gathered out of the judicious treatises of William Bates, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Hopkins, Ezekiel, 1634-1690.</author>
                  <author>Bates, William, 1625-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 132, 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ..., Jonathan Robinson ..., and Tho. Cockeril ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: "The upright Christian" (22 p. at end) is lacking on film.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXVI --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXVIII --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Almoſt Chriſtian DISCOVERED, In ſome SERMONS on <hi>Acts</hi> 26.28. With a Blow at Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>By the R. R. <hi>Ezekiel Hopkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, The <hi>Upright CHRISTIAN</hi> DISCOVERED: Gathered out of the judicious Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey, Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church Yard, and <hi>Tho. Cockeril</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Excellent Preacher of theſe Sermons, was one that <hi>ſought out acceptable Words;</hi> not to tickle the Fancy, but to affect the Conſciences, in order to better the Hearts and Lives of his Auditors. He was a Perſon truly great and good; well known, not only in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> (where he ſhined in a higher Orb) but in this of <hi>England</hi> alſo, eſpecially in the two Renowned Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (not only for Trade, but Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Exeter,</hi> where Multitudes ſate under his Miniſtry with great Delight and Profit. I need
<pb facs="tcp:49760:3"/>not trouble my ſelf or the Reader to make ſolemn Proteſtations, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert Certificates under the Hands of ſeveral Perſons concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentickneſs of theſe Sermons: All thoſe that have heard him, or have read his other excellent and uſeful Treatiſes (a large Account of which, is here annexed) will eaſily be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by the Spirituality of the Matter, and Beauty of the Stile, that theſe are the genuine Offspring of Biſhop <hi>Hopkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe Diſcourſes may be ſo bleſs'd to all that ſhall read them, that they may be not only <hi>Almoſt,</hi> but <hi>Altogether Chriſtians,</hi> is the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prayer of the Publiſher.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:3"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE OF THE Works of Biſhop <hi>Hopkins</hi> alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Publiſhed.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Vanity of the World;</hi> in ſeveral Sermons, from <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Vanity of Vanities, ſaith the Preacher; Vanity of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, all is Vanity.</hi> To which is added Two other Sermons; one at the Funeral of the Honourable <hi>Algernoon Grevil</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> from <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.5. <hi>For the Living know that they ſhall die.</hi> The other, on the 30th. of <hi>January,</hi> from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.14. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake whether it be to the King as ſupream, or unto Governours, as unto them
<pb facs="tcp:49760:4"/>who are ſent by him, for the puniſhment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil doers, and the praiſe of them that do wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes, or Sermons on ſeveral Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Vol.</hi> I. Containing theſe following Subjects;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Folly of Sinners in making a mock of Sin;</hi> from <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Fools make a mock at Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24. <hi>Whom God hath raiſed up, having looſed the pains of Death, becauſe it was not poſſible that he ſhould be holden of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>True Happineſs;</hi> from <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in through the Gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brotherly Admonition;</hi> from <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart; thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Dreadfulneſs of God's Wrath againſt Sinners;</hi> Demonſtrated from <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.30, 31. <hi>For we know him that hath ſaid, Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance belongeth unto me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord: And again the Lord ſhall judge his People. It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; To which is added two Sermons; one on St. <hi>John</hi> 7.19. <hi>Did not Moſes give you the Law, and yet none of you keepeth the Law.</hi> The other, on <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3 10. <hi>For as many as are of the works of the Law, are under the Curſe of the Law; for it is written, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the Book of the Law to do them.</hi> In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the Lord's Prayer, with a Catechiſtical Explication thereof, by way of Queſtion and Anſwer for the inſtructing of Youth: To which is added, <hi>A Diſcourſe upon Providence;</hi> from St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29, 30. <hi>Are not two Sparrows ſold for a farthing, and one of them ſhall not fall to the ground without your Father? But the very hairs of your head are all numbred.</hi> As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:49760:5"/>A Diſcourſe demonſtrating the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Advantages of reading and ſtudying the Holy Scriptures; from <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all Wiſdom.</hi> In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second Volume of Diſcourſes or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on ſeveral Scriptures; containing theſe following Subjects, <hi>viz. A Diſcourſe on Man's Mortality;</hi> from <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>It is appointed unto Men once to die, and after this the Judgment. The great Evil and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of little Sins;</hi> from St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall break any one of theſe leaſt Commandments, and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Of Abſtaining from the Appearance of Evil,</hi> from 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Abſtain from all appearance of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Nature, Danger, Aggravations and Cure of preſumptuous Sinning, with the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Reſtraining and ſanctifying Grace; from Preſumptuous Sins;</hi> from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Keep back thy Servant from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Sins, let them not have dominion over me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Pardon and Forgiveneſs of Sin;</hi> from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.25. <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy Tranſgreſſions for my own ſake, and will not remember thy Sins.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several other Diſcourſes of this Reverend Biſhop's are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned ſhortly to be Printed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49760:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49760:6"/>
            <head>SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 26.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Paul</hi> ALMOST thou perſuadeſt me to be a CHRISTIAN.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter we have St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Fetters pleading before that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Seſſions of <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa;</hi> his Plea we have largely ſet down from the 1ſt. to the 24th. Verſe, in which he opens his Commiſſion, that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in an extraordinary manner from Heaven, for preaching of that Doctrine which was every where ſpoken againſt, and for worſhipping God in that way which was called Hereſie. I ſhall not at all enter into the conſideration of the Apology; but let us look only at the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Effects that it wrought upon the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49760:7"/>Hearers: <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa</hi> they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both of them Unbelievers, the one an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> believing <hi>Heathen,</hi> the other an unbeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Jew,</hi> and thus they both continue yet St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Speech works very different<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon them. In the 24th. Verſe you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Feſtus</hi> raving; he <hi>ſaid with a loud voic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paul, thou art beſides<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelf, much learni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath made thee mad.</hi> Thy Thoughts of Viſion and an Apparition, of a Man dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and buried, lying ſafe under ground that he ſhould riſe again and appear fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heaven to thee, being the Saviour of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World, is a meer Fancy, proceeding fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſtrong Phrenzy: Thus he ſcoffs an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> raves. But this very Sermon which ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Madneſs and an idle Tale to unbeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Feſtus,</hi> carries a ſtrong Convicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in it to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who was an Unbeliev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> too; <hi>Almost thou perſuadeſt me to be Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence obſerve <hi>That the Word of God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a far different effect, even upon thoſe, up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom it hath no ſaving effect;</hi> one raves a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rageth againſt it, is ſeared and ſtupiſie by it; another is convinced and terriſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by it. <hi>Feſtus</hi> he ſcoffs and mocks, go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away laughing at the Doctrine, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> viling the Preacher: But <hi>Agrippa</hi> is co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49760:7"/>and half perſuaded, to believe and practiſe that very Doctrine, and highly to eſteem the Preacher of it. And is it not ſo even among us? Are there not many who may come to the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a natural and ſinful Eſtate and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the ſame Word of God is caſt among them all; yea, but what is the Succeſs? The <hi>Sword of the Spirit</hi> when it is <hi>brandiſhed</hi> amongſt a great Croud of Conſciences, it is not likely that it ſhould miſs all, and ſtrike none of them; one perhaps goes away ſlighting and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; another goes away ſcoffing and railing againſt it; and another half-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded by it to become a Chriſtian, to be almoſt a Chriſtian. If every Man's Breaſt had a Caſement in it by which we might ſee the inward Eſtuations and Boilings of their Hearts, how they work after a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and terrifying Sermon; ſhould we not behold and ſee ſome ſhifting, and ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling their Sins out of the way; ſome holding up the Bucklers of prejudicate Opinions, to ward and fence off the ſtroke of the Spirit; ſome fretting and ſtorming at the lancing of their Conſciences; ſome ſcorning and ſcoffing with <hi>Feſtus,</hi> that it is no better than Folly and Madneſs; ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49760:8"/>trembling with <hi>Felix;</hi> ſome convinced and wrought upon as <hi>Agrippa</hi> to faint reſolutions, and half purpoſes; and yet all theſe remain under the Power of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and Unregeneracy. It is indeed a wonder among ſuch diverſity of Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the Word hath upon the Souls and Conſciences of Men, it could be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ſuch a multitude ſhould go away without any ſaving Operation by it; ſome blinded and hardened, ſome terrified, ſome ſtupified; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e exaſperated and inraged; ſome convinced and half-perſuaded, and ſuch are thoſe that we now ſpeak of: Such as are, as it were, half of one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and half of another, that ſtick in the New Birth, whoſe Hearts have been warmed with good Motions; who have entertained approving and admiring Thoughts concerning the ways of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who have taken up ſome reſolutions of doing better, and of being better; and yet do not come off roundly and ſpeedily from their Sins, nor cloſe fully with Chriſt. Theſe are the half-Chriſtians which the Text ſpeaks of.</p>
            <p>The Words they are plain in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and therefore do not require
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49760:8"/>much Explication. Only the Word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>Almoſt</hi> thou perſuadeſt me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if accurately rendered according to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, it is <hi>a little</hi> thou perſuadeſt me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So in the Reply St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes with a holy kind of Gallantry in the enſuing Verſe you find there it is oppoſed to <hi>much,</hi> which we render <hi>altogether;</hi> but the Grammatical Conſtruction is, Would to God they were both <hi>all and in much</hi> ſuch as I am except theſe Bonds. So then <hi>in a little</hi> thou perſuadeſt me; that is, I could methinks be contented to be a Chriſtian <hi>in a little,</hi> in ſome few things; ſome part of the Way I could willingly go, ſaith <hi>Agrippa:</hi> But St. <hi>Paul</hi> concludes, it muſt not be only in a little, but in much, in all. If we follow this Sence and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Words; then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>There goes much to the making of a true Chriſtian, a little will not ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not a little will ſerve; for many precious Ingredients go to the making of a true Chriſtian; and much of each In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient goes to the making of a ſtrong Chriſtian. There muſt be Profeſſion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49760:9"/>Faith, Obedience, Self-denial, Patience, Humility, outward Preparation and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Graces, outward Imbelliſhments and inward Ornaments, and a little of it is but little worth. There are many that are perſuaded to be Chriſtians in Name and Profeſſion, to be Chriſtians in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward participation of Ordinances and Communion with Saints and the like; yea, but this is to be a Chriſtian but only in a little. Are you perſuaded to obey Chriſt in all, to take up his Croſs, and deny your ſelves, to oppoſe and mortifie your Luſts, and to perform the harſheſt and ſevereſt part of Religion: This is indeed to be a Chriſtian not only in a little but in much; yea, in all, to be ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was. But then if you take the <hi>Words</hi> according to our Tranſlation, which the Original alſo will very well bear. So it is within a little or <hi>almost</hi> thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadeſt me; for King <hi>Agrippa</hi> was fully convinced of the Truth of thoſe things which <hi>Paul</hi> related, as you may ſee, <hi>v.</hi> 26. He knew theſe things, and was ignorant of none of them, they were not hidden from him; for theſe things were not done in a corner. He could not be ignorant of the miraculous Converſion of him, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49760:9"/>had been ſo furious and notorious a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Chriſtians: He, who was expert in all the Cuſtoms that were among the <hi>Jews, ver.</hi> 3. could not be ignorant of what the Apoſtle affirms, <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. This that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets foretold that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer and be raiſed from the dead, and ſhould give life to the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> Of all this King <hi>Agrippa</hi> was fully convinced; and yet when <hi>Paul</hi> ſo inſinuatingly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon him, <hi>Believeſt thou the Prophets? I know thou believeſt.</hi> The reſult of all is this, That he was but almoſt perſuaded, not fully perſuaded of the Truth of what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks concerning Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelf, and concerning Chriſtians; yet for all that he was but <hi>almost perſuaded</hi> to be a Chriſtian. Hence likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That Perſons who are fully and truly convinced, are many times but almoſt and half-perſuaded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a powerful perſuaſion in the Judgment and the Conſcience concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt and his ways, when there is but half a perſuaſion in the Will and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to cloſe with him. Theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49760:10"/>I gather up as they lie ſtrewed in my paſſage. I ſhall not inſiſt upon them but only as they are ſubſervient to the fuller Proſecution of the General Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which you may take thus.</p>
            <p>Doct. 3. <hi>That thoſe who never were in CHRIST; yet may be almoſt Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not here ſtand to tell you, that Chriſtianity may be taken either,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For an <hi>outward Profeſſion</hi> of Chriſt, as it is oppoſed to all other Religions in the World, whether <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Idolatry, <hi>Mahometan</hi> Stupidity, or <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For <hi>an inward and cordial em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> thus profeſſed, as it ſtands oppoſed, either to the Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Hypocriſie of carnal Goſpellers.</p>
            <p>Evident it is, that the Chriſtianity that <hi>Agrippa</hi> was almoſt perſuaded into, was of the firſt ſort, not excluding the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. Nay, it was ſeldom ſeen that in thoſe Primitive Times, wherein no car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reſpect or outward Advantage could
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49760:10"/>commend the Goſpel to the Intereſts of Men. When the reward of profeſſing Chriſt was Perſecution and Martyrdom; then I ſay it was ſeldom ſeen that any would take Chriſt by Profeſſion, who would not alſo take him by Faith and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence. Few there were that would take up Religion, even upon this Condition, to lay down their Lives for Chriſt, who yet through their own Profaneneſs or Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, were to receive no Benefit from the Death of Chriſt. So that to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade Men then to be Chriſtians in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, it was the ſame with perſuading them to be Chriſtians in reality. <q>But now when the Name of Chriſt is ſo much courted, when the denying of Chriſt would be repaid with the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that formerly the owning of Chriſt underwent, you need not ſo much perſuaſion to take upon you the outward Profeſſion of Chriſtianity.</q> For you are not only <hi>almoſt,</hi> but <hi>altogether</hi> Chriſtians in the external Garb; but our perſuaſion to you, muſt be, that as you own Chriſt in an outward Profeſſion of him, ſo that you would cleave to him by a true Faith in him, and Obedience to him.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49760:11"/>
            <p>We are not then to ſpeak to <hi>Pagans,</hi> to convert them to a new Religion; but (if I may ſo ſay) we are to ſpeak to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Infidels, to convert them to a new Life and Converſation. Nor yet among theſe doth my Subject lead me to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and looſer ſort, whoſe being called Chriſtians doth not more honour them, than they diſgrace and reproach that holy Name; but to thoſe who are more ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, and more refined, who go far in Chriſtianity ſo as to be near the Kingdom of God. In a word, ſuch as are <hi>Almoſt Chriſtians,</hi> and yet are Strangers to Chriſt, and remain in their ſinful State and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Condition.</p>
            <p>Now in the Proſecution of this Point, I ſhall enquire into theſe following Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in this Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What <hi>Progreſs</hi> Men may make towards Chriſtianity, and yet fall ſhort of it.</item>
               <item>2. Whence they are enabled to proceed ſo far, and what it is that carries them out to all their Attainments.</item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49760:11"/>
               <item>3. What it is that hinders them from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding further; and when they are <hi>almoſt</hi> Chriſtians, what keeps them from being ſuch <hi>altogether?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. To ſhew you the folly and miſery of thoſe who proceed thus far only, as to be almoſt Chriſtians, and no farther.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us ſee <hi>what Progreſs a natural. Man may make towards Grace</hi> and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and yet remain in a ſinful ſtate. Before I can come in particular to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this, I muſt premiſe theſe two or three Particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That when we enquire what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs an unregenerate man may make towards Grace, this ſuppoſes that there is a tendency in what ſuch a man doth, or may do towards the obtaining of Grace. Or how elſe can he make any progreſs towards it, if that which he doth hath no tendency to it? Let us therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what kind of tendency this is. There may be a two-ſold tendency ſuppoſed in the Actions of an unregenerate man, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the acquiſition of Grace.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49760:12"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. Effective, Tendency.</item>
               <item>2. Subjective, Tendency.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. Actions may be ſaid to have an <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive tendency,</hi> when they do by their own efficiency and cauſalty produce that which they tend to; and in this ſence it muſt be denied that the Actions of an unregenerate man, have any tendency towards Grace, be their progreſs what it will; thereby he cannot efficiently produce or cauſe Grace in himſelf; and therefore Grace is called the new Creature, as being the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect only of creating Power, which is the ſole Prerogative of God, and it is as utterly impoſſible for a Man to create Grace in the Soul, as to create the Soul it ſelf. Take but this one demonſtration to evince it: If an unregenerate Man by his own Power and Efficiency can produce Grace in himſelf, then one of theſe two groſs Abſurdities muſt needs follow, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 1. that there are ſtill left holy Habits and Principles in the Will, which were never loſt by the Fall of Man: Or, 2. That a Man may make himſelf truly holy by a Will that is totally corrupt and ſinful; but either of theſe are very groſs.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49760:12"/>
            <p>Firſt, There are no holy nor divine Habits left in the <hi>Will</hi> of a <hi>carnal man,</hi> whereby he ſhould be able to regenerate, and convert himſelf; for what holy Habit can there be in the Will of one that is wholly corrupted? if any ſuch be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it may alſo be ſuppoſed that it is true Grace; and to affirm that a Man in a ſtate of Nature hath true Grace inherent in him, whereby he is able to convert and regenerate himſelf, is double non-ſence and a flat contradiction; for it is to affirm that he hath Grace before he hath it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Will totally corrupted, cannot make an holy Man, cannot produce Grace, nor make a Man holy, Grace is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond and above its Sphere, all the motions of the Will in its fallen Eſtate, what through defect of a right Principle from whence they flow, and a right <hi>end</hi> to which they tend, they are all evil and ſinful. And it is very ſtrange to affirm that a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Habit may be wrought in us by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Actions. And beſides the Will of a Man by the Fall, it is a fleſhly Will; but in Regeneration it is made ſpiritual. Now it were a ſtrange kind of Production, if fleſhly could beget ſpiritual; nor would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49760:13"/>it any longer hold true what our Saviour ſaith in <hi>John</hi> 3.35. <hi>That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh:</hi> So that I think 'tis very evident, that all that a Man can do by the power of Nature cannot tend efficiently to produce Grace in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a <hi>ſubjective tendency</hi> towards Grace; and this lies in thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preparations, and thoſe diſpoſitions of the heart which fit it for the receiving of Grace, though it be wrought there only by the Holy Ghoſt. And thus we affirm that while Men are in an unregenerate ſtate, they may have and do ſomewhat that hath a tendency in it to Grace; that is, one unregenerate Man may have more of theſe previous diſpoſitions, and of theſe preparations for the receiving of Grace, than another hath: For though it be not in it ſelf ſingly neceſſary that ſuch <hi>previous</hi> diſpoſitions ſhould be wrought in the Soul before the implantation of divine Grace; ſince ſuch a Subject as the Soul is in reſpect of Grace, doth not, as the Schoolmen deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, require its previous diſpoſitions for the production of its Form; yet this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the uſual common way of the Spirit's work,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To prepare the heart by ſome common Works of Conviction, legal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49760:13"/>Terrors, and remorſe of Conſcience, firſt to prepare the heart by theſe before it works any ſaving and real work of Grace in it: And therefore when any unregenerate man hath much of theſe previous prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we ſay that he goes <hi>very</hi> far towards Grace, and he may be ſaid to be <hi>almoſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi> And this is all that tendency that an unregenerate Man hath, or can poſſibly do towards it; <hi>viz.</hi> a preparatory, and not an effective operative tendency unto ſaving Grace and Regeneration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thing premiſed is this, That what through wilful ſloth and <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed negligence,</hi> no unregenerate Man doth make ſo great a progreſs towards Grace as he is able and can poſſibly do. None go ſo far as they can do in thoſe previous preparations and diſpoſitions towards it. When they find difficulty in oppoſing Temptation, in crucifying their Luſts, in performing of Duties, in denying their ſinful Delights and Pleaſures, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſupernatural within them to natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and facilitate theſe things, and carry them on reſolutely through all, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver keep up to the utmoſt of that Power which they have; but as they yield to thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49760:14"/>Temptations that they might reſiſt, and commit thoſe Sins that they might reject, and neglect thoſe Duties which for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Subſtance of them they might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; ſo none of them goes ſo far as they have a natural power to do: No Man goes ſo far in the work of Grace as he might, if he would improve that power which he hath by Nature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Did they make as great a progreſs towards Grace as they might, they would not fall ſo far ſhort of Grace as they do. I ſay if a wicked unregenerate Man did but as much as he is able by the power of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to do, without the ſpecial Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, they would not fall ſo far ſhort of Grace as they do. I would not enter into that Diſpute whether God be engaged to beſtow Grace upon the right Improvement of their natural power; yet it is certain, and agreed on by all, that he doth certainly do ſo. God uſually beſtows true and ſaving Grace upon thoſe who do rightly, and to their utmoſt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their natural power and ability for their acquiring of it. If God be not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by promiſe to aſſiſt them; yet through his Goodneſs and Mercy he is not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49760:14"/>wont to deſert them. Let them but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to improve their natural ability to the utmoſt ſtrain and pitch that their own capacity can elevate, God will (according to his uſual method and wonted Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) come in by ſupernatural Grace, and inable them to do that which by Nature they are not able to do; for no inſtance can be given to the contrary. So then we may conclude that wicked Men never go ſo far as they can; and did they, yet they could not efficiently work Grace in themſelves, but nevertheleſs they would be diſpoſed and prepared for the receipt of Grace, which God upon ſuch prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations would undoubtedly beſtow upon them. For although he be not obliged to give it them, yet uſually he is wont to work it in them meerly through his own natural Goodneſs, free Grace and Mercy to them, pitying the weakneſs of their lapſed and fallen Nature.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed to the Anſwer of the firſt Queſtion in the general. 1. Unregenerate Men may make a great progreſs, and may go very far towards Grace, and yet fall ſhort of it; that in general is to be <hi>Almoſt a Chrſtian.</hi> This I laid down in the Method propounded to you. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49760:15"/>though I ſay not they go as far as they can by the power of Nature, and yet fall ſhort of Grace; for that can never be inſtanced in any; yet the ſad and wretched Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of thoſe who have been eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, ſhining, yea, and glaring Lights, exceeding, and alſo deſpiſing common attainments of others; their Apoſtacy hath too evidently confirmed it to us, that Men may go very far towards Grace, and yet fall ſhort of it. See what Chriſt ſaith <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.24. of that young Man, that forward young Man, <hi>Thou art not far from the Kingdom of God;</hi> that is, thou art not far from Grace; for ſo the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is oftentimes taken in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for the Kingdom of Grace, ſo that we may ſay of ſuch Men, they were not far from the Kingdom of God, not far from Grace, not far from Heaven, climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up almoſt thither, within view and ken of it, having one foot, as it were, upon the Threſhold of the Heavenly Gate; and yet even theſe tumble headlong, and never reſt until they have plunged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the bottom of Hell. It is with ſuch Men as it is with the Vapours that are drawn up into the Air, they ſhine with the ſame Light, with the ſame appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49760:15"/>Magnitude as the fixed Stars them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do, and we may think them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the very ſame Sphere with them; but when we ſee them dart down to the Earth, and ſpilling all that Light and Glory, which they gliſtered with by the way, and fall into a filthy Jelly, thicker and more loathſome Subſtance than when they were firſt exhaled, we then conclude that all that Elevation of thoſe falſe and blazing Lights, was vaſtly ſhort of that Heaven in which they ſeemed ſometime to be fixed. So is it with many unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Men; you cannot tell with what they are fraught till you ſee them ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracked; then it is a ſign, that though they were never right and true Treaſure, yet they are ſomething very like it: When we ſee them tumbling down off a glorious Profeſſion through fatal Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pices of great, groſs, and deſperate Sins, we may ſadly conclude that that Man was not far from the Kingdom of God, though he was never yet there. Indeed every unregenerate Man, when he winds up himſelf to the higheſt pitch and ſtrain, he may be ſaid to be far from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, in reſpect of his total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of Grace; though his Actions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49760:16"/>be never ſo fair and ſpecious, yet they are very far from being gracious, as far as <hi>Darkneſs</hi> is from Light; yet he may be ſaid not to be far from the Kingdom of God likewiſe in a four-fold reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In that he is far from that which is furtheſt from Grace; and that is, groſs, flagitious, and notorious Sins, which are fartheſt off from Grace of all others; and theſe a natural Man may be very far and free from; and therefore not far from Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He may have that which very much reſembles and counterfeits Grace, ſo that as to outward appearance there is but very little Diſſimilitude diſcernable between them. Now that which is like another, may be ſaid not to be far from that which it is like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He may be ſaid not to be far from Grace, becauſe (as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) in the ordinary Works of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon his Soul, he may have thoſe preparations and diſpoſitions laid in them, which uſually are previous and antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Grace, becauſe theſe are wrought
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49760:16"/>uſually before Grace; and therefore the perſon that hath theſe wrought upon him may be ſaid not to be far from Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He may be ſaid not to be far from Grace, becauſe if he did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed but a little farther, he would poſſibly attain to true Grace. Had ſuch but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved their natural power to ſuch a degree farther, God would have come in with power ſupernatural, and have wrought that true and ſaving Principle in their lives, which would have been ſure to have brought them to eternal Life. Grace indeed hath ſuch a kind of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon that which is <hi>natural;</hi> and that dependance is not ſo much of <hi>Cauſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as of Order and Conſequence, which though it be not neceſſary, yet it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly granted on all Hands. Thus then in the general I have ſhewn you that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Men may go far, yea very far towards. A Man may be <hi>Almoſt</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and yet be out of Chriſt; be near the Kingdom of Heaven, and yet not in it; and, poſſibly, be for ever excluded and ſhut out of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49760:17"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I ſhall proceed to the next thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. As we have ſeen in the general, ſo now let us conſider in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar what <hi>Progreſs</hi> a natural Man may make towards <hi>Grace;</hi> and that I ſhall do, by conſidering the ſeveral ſteps and degrees by which they may ariſe up to a great height and glory of outward Profeſſion: And this we cannot better do, than by ſhewing, 1. What Grace is. 2. What reſemblance that which is wrought by a meer carnal Man may carry in it like true Grace; by comparing theſe together, we may ſee how near an unregenerate, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man may come to true and ſaving Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> What <hi>Grace</hi> is. I need not tell you that I ſpeak not now of an <hi>Objective Grace</hi> inherent in God; but terminated on us, whereby a change is wrought in our relation to him. And this <hi>Objective Grace</hi> is nothing elſe but the divine Love, Favour, and good Will of God expreſſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49760:17"/>in us. But I ſpeak of <hi>a Subjective Grace</hi> inherent in us; whereby a real change is made in our Lives and Natures. And in brief you may take this Deſcription of ſubjective or inherent Grace: It is a ſupernatural Habit immediately infuſed into the Soul by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> reſiding in every Power and Faculty of the Soul as a Principle of holy and ſpiritual Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And there is a five-fold change wrought by it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Upon <hi>the Judgment, or the direct <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> by informing and enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</item>
               <item>2. Upon <hi>the Conſcience</hi> in the reflex Underſtanding, by awakening and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying it.</item>
               <item>3. Upon <hi>the Affections,</hi> by ſpiritualizing them.</item>
               <item>4. Upon <hi>the Will,</hi> by converting it.</item>
               <item>5. Upon <hi>the Life and Converſation,</hi> by reforming it.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49760:18"/>
            <p>This five-fold change is wrought upon the whole Soul by true and ſanctifying Grace.</p>
            <p>Now in the next place I ſhall ſhew how far a natural Man may attain to theſe, ſo as to be <hi>Almoſt a Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, As for his Mind or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> he may be <hi>irradiated with a clear and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling knowledge of divine and ſpiritual Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> when yet the Soul is not truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to God. It is true as in the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the World, the Light is numbered and reckoned amongſt the firſt of God's Works: So likewiſe in this new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the firſt work of the Spirit of God is to ſhed abroad his heavenly Light it the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and therefore we have this firſt in order, in that Commiſſion which our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt gives to St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 26.18. He ſent him to the <hi>Gentiles, to open their eyes, and to turn then from darkneſs to light;</hi> and then it follows, <hi>from the power of Satan to God.</hi> But yet notwithſtanding, there is an Illumination about ſpiritual Things, which may <hi>gil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>beautifie</hi> the Underſtanding of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man, who like a Toad may be full
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49760:18"/>of Poiſon, though he hath a precious Stone in his Head. The Apoſtle, he lays down this as one of thoſe Attainments that an unregenerate Man may have, and yet be an Apoſtate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. he may not only have a deep knowledge of Goſpel-Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo as to ſee the whole Compages and concatenation of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and to unfold them to others; but may have alſo particular diſcoveries of the Glory and Beauty that there is in theſe things. We may ſee it clearly by <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Ecſtaſie, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24. Such diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries carnal hearts may have made to them, and ſee their Luſtre and Beauty. Nay further, a carnal Man may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that there is no other way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery but by the Grace of God through the Merits of Chriſt, and of the ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt to his Soul, of the Freeneſs of God's <hi>Love,</hi> of the Riches of his <hi>Grace,</hi> of the <hi>Readineſs</hi> of his <hi>Heart</hi> to receive them; of the Deſirableneſs of Happineſs, of the Beauty of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and yet for all this remain in a natural State: But now, not to leave you under doubts and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, ſuch an <hi>Illumination</hi> of a carnal Man, falls far ſhort of true Grace in theſe Two Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49760:19"/>
            <p>Firſt, In that it is but <hi>Lumen ſterile, a barren light;</hi> Illumination that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, is not only Light, but influence too.</p>
            <p>As the Light of the Sun doth not ſerve only to <hi>paint the World,</hi> and <hi>varniſh</hi> over the <hi>Beauty</hi> and Variety of ſeveral Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that are in it; but carries in it <hi>a grateful heat and cheriſhing influence,</hi> which operates into them, and refreſheth them; and as the Light diſcovers their Beauty, ſo theſe Influences increaſe it: So ſaving <hi>Illumination,</hi> not only <hi>illuſtrates</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> by its Light; but likewiſe, by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genialneſs</hi> of its Influences, nouriſhes the Soul, draws Sap into it, and Fruit from it. Such is not the Illumination of an unregenerate Man; it is but a barren Light, and only ſerves to paint his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and hath no influence on it to make the Soul <hi>grow in Grace, and bring forth the Fruits of Holineſs, to the Praiſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Illumination</hi> that is <hi>ſaving</hi> is <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. <hi>We all, as in a Glaſs, behold the Glory of the Lord, and are changed into the ſame Image,</hi> &amp;c. If a Beam of the Sun falls upon a Looking-Glaſs, it not only makes it <hi>glitter</hi> with a glorious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49760:19"/>Light, but it repreſents the very Image of the Sun in the Glaſs; but let it beat never ſo clearly and ſtrongly upon a Mud-Wall, though it enlightens it, yet it doth not thereby leave its Image upon it. So truly Illumination, that is ſaving, doth not only <hi>irradiate,</hi> but transform. If you look upon the Sun, when ſhining in its ſtrength, the Light thereof will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the very Shape and Image of the Sun upon your Eye; and look where you will, ſtill you retain the appearance of the Sun before you: So every ſight that a true Chriſtian hath of the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, will make as it were another Sun in his Soul. <hi>But now the Illumination of wicked Men doth only enlighten, not change them; their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings may be irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diated with glorious Diſcoveries of God, Chriſt, and the Things of Heaven;</hi> but this doth not transform them into the Image and Likeneſs of thoſe Things. The Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of godly Men and true Chriſtians, is like the Light which breaks through the Air, and turns every vaſt Body throughout the World all into Light. It is with wicked, unregenerate Men, as with thoſe that lie long in the Sun-ſhine; which though it inlightens them, yet doth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49760:20"/>but afterwards make them more black and ſwarthy. So thou may'ſt have as much notional Knowledge of God, Chriſt, and the Myſteries of the Goſpel as any Child of God hath, and poſſibly much more, yet this is no true Sign of Grace; for this Knowledge is not therefore ſaving, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is clear and comprehenſive, but becauſe it is influential and transforming. And uſually we perceive that where the Light of Knowledge ſhines into a wicked Heart, it doth but <hi>tann</hi> and make the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more black and ſwarthy, more ſinful than before: Thus, as to the <hi>direct <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> of the Judgment, a natural Man may have a bright, clear, and glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Light concerning Heavenly and ſpiritual Objects.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As for the <hi>Reflex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> of the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Neither yet the Peace nor the Trouble of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is ſuch an Attainment to which a natural Mar cannot reach.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>natural</hi> Man may have <hi>a quiet</hi> and <hi>peaceable Conſcience.</hi> Indeed when this Peace is true, it is always an effect of Grace; and therefore we thus find the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49760:20"/>coupled together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. Yet there is that which looks very like Peace of Conſcience though it be not ſuch, and that is a <hi>ſupine</hi> Preſumption and a carnal Stupidity and Oſcitancy: Their Conſciences are never troubled at the ſight of Sin, or ſenſe of Wrath; but are like thoſe preſumptuous Sinners ſpoken of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>And it come to paſs when he heareth the words of this Curſe, that he bleſs himſelf in his Heart, ſaying, I ſhall have peace, tho I walk in the Imagination of mine Heart,</hi> &amp;c. Now this Peace is founded only upon bold and confident Perſuaſions of God's infinite Mercy, and gracious Diſpoſition; and becauſe God will exalt his Mercy above all his Name, therefore they conclude; that as God hath exalted his Power in creating and ſuſtaining them, ſo he will much more exalt his <hi>Mercy</hi> in ſaving them. Thus as <hi>Mad-men</hi> often fanſie themſelves Kings or ſome great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, when indeed they are but wretched and miſerable Spectacles, ſo do theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Mad-men; and as the Devil appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priates to himſelf all the Glory of the Earth, ſo theſe look upon Heaven, and all the Glory of it, and boldly call it all their own; yea, and through their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49760:21"/>wretched Security, are bold to cry out with <hi>Thomas, My Lord, and my God.</hi> To ſuch I may ſay with our Saviour in another Caſe, <hi>God is not the God of the dead, but the God of the living.</hi> God is not the God of ſuch as love, and live in their Sins and Luſts; and that call him Father, whom yet they diſhonour by a lewd and diſſolute Life: This is but <hi>is Father one of the Devil's Off-ſpring upon the holy God.</hi> Indeed Men by enormous and flagitious Crimes have ſo wounded and waſted their Conſciences, that now they retain not ſtrength enough to accuſe, moleſt, and trouble them; and this they call Peace of Conſcience: Such a Peace as <hi>Gallious</hi> (in <hi>Tacitus</hi>) exprobrates the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> with, when they have laid all waſte. This they call Peace; but this Peace is rather <hi>deadneſs</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and is far from that which ariſeth from the true Grace of God; and that that is the work of the Holy Ghoſt in Conviction, which deſtroys this ill-grounded Peace; and it works in the Soul Horrors and Terrors, and affrights the ſecure Soul when it ſhews it how it ſlept upon the Top of the Maſt, and lay on the very Brink of the Infernal Pit. As therefore we muſt not diſcourage
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49760:21"/>a broken Spirit, but embolden it to appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Chriſt, and all the Promiſes of the Goſpel to it ſelf in particular; ſo we muſt let wicked Men know, that when they preſume to call God, their God and their Father, and yet continue in their Sins and Wickedneſs, they will find that inſtead of being their Father, he will only be their Judge.</p>
            <p>Now it will appear that this Peace of a carnal Man is only from deep Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the Spirit of Slumber that hath ſeized upon them; becauſe when we come to examine the grounds of it, they plead only the goodneſs of their Hearts, and there is nothing more familiar and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent than this they boaſt of; and though they live in a conſtant neglect of holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and wallow in the Filth of cuſtomary Sins, yet ſtill they boaſt of this, that they have very good Hearts, upright In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. This is a meer deluſion; for it is as utterly impoſſible that the Heart ſhould be good when the Life is wicked and prophane, as for a good Root to bring forth evil and corrupt Fruit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be attained by natural Men, ſo many times
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49760:22"/>ſuch may lie under the Regrets and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Conſcience. It is not Trouble of Conſcience that is the Attainment where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in true Grace doth conſiſt: A dull and a lethargick Conſcience that hath long lain under the cuſtomary Commiſſion of groſs Sins, may at length, by ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, be ſtartled and awakened to a ſenſe of Sin, and be affraid at the ſight of it; but yet may retain an impure and defiled Conſcience: God may (even in this Life) kindle in their Breaſts ſome Sparks of the <hi>unquenchable Fire,</hi> and may give them ſome fore-taſts of that Cup of Trembling that they muſt for ever drink of. As he hath made himſelf a Devil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate by his Sin, ſo God may make his Conſcience a Hell incarnate. By his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience you hear <hi>Cain,</hi> that Primitive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, crying out, my Puniſhment is greater than I can bear; nor could <hi>Judas</hi> find any other way to check his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence but with an Halter: Theſe Regrets of Conſcience may proceed from a preparatory work of Conviction, which becauſe of Men's wilful deſerting them, often vaniſh away without any ſaving ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and fall as far ſhort of true Grace, as the Region of the Air where Storms
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49760:22"/>and Tempeſts, Thunderings and Lightnings are ingendered, falls ſhort of the Heaven of the Bleſſed, and that Eternal calmneſs and ſerenity: And as Worms uſually are the off-ſpring of corruption and putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; ſo this <hi>never dying Worm,</hi> that muſt ever ſting them, oftentimes in this life, is bred out of a rotten and corrupted Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the Conſcience therefore may be defiled, when it is not ſeared; it may be awakened, when it is not ſanctified; a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy puddle may be ſtirred as well as a clear running ſtream, the Conſcience may work terrors and horrors, where the Spirit of God never wrought true ſaving Grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As to the <hi>Affections:</hi> There may be Affections and ſweet Motions of the Heart, which are oftentimes relyed on us certain evidences of true Grace; yet alſo may be in a carnal and natural <hi>Man, Mat.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Some received the word with joy,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>John.</hi> 5. Chriſt tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> they did for a ſeaſon rejoyce in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Preaching of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. Thus <hi>Herod</hi> is ſaid to hear <hi>John</hi> gladly, ſo that you ſee the Affections in holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Ordinances may be with joy, even
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49760:23"/>in thoſe that have no true Grace at all in them. As there may be thoſe affections of joy and delight, ſo likewiſe of ſorrow for ſin, ſo we have it 27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. It is ſaid of <hi>Judas,</hi> he repented himſelf, and <hi>Ahab</hi>'s humiliation was ſo great, that God takes ſpecial notice of him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. Behold, how <hi>Ahab</hi> humbleth himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How all theſe affections are but tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and vaniſhing, which may be excited, even in carnal Men, from ſeveral advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that things have to commend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to their judgments and to their hearts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Sometimes the very <hi>novelty,</hi> and the ſtrangeneſs of them may affect them: <hi>Novelty</hi> uſually breeds delight, which lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger cuſtom and acquaintance doth abate, and this may be given as a reaſon, why ſoon after converſion the new Converts affections are drawn forth more ſtrongly in the ways of God, more than afterwards when they grow ſettled and ſtable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; the reaſon is, becauſe of the very novelty of that courſe and way they have now entered into, which affects them with delight, beſides the real deſirableneſs which is in thoſe ways themſelves; the very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49760:23"/>doth affect them, and this too may ſatisfie us, that though many are turned aſide from the truth as it is in Jeſus Chriſt, and from the way of Worſhip which God hath appointed us, that have boaſted, that they have found more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and more ſweet affections than ever, in thoſe new ways after which they have gone; yet it is not becauſe thoſe ways have any thing in them, that might yield them more comfort and delight, but only becauſe they are new ways, and all new things will for the preſent ſtir up the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but after ſome continuance in thoſe ways, they find their joy and their delight to ſlag; then they ſeek out other new ways, and commend them as much; and no wonder, for new ways will ſtir up new affections; that may be one Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why affections may be ſtirred up, even in the unregenerate and meer carnal Men, as to the things of God, even from the meer novelty of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Good affections may be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in Men, from the very <hi>affecting nature</hi> of ſpiritual Objects themſelves; for ſpiritual Objects may affect us in this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way. Who can read <hi>the Hiſtory of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49760:24"/>Chriſt's Paſſion,</hi> without being affected with ſorrow, for all the ſorrow he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went; he hath a heart harder than Rocks, that can hear of the Agonies, and Scourges, and cruel Indignities offered to ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and excellent a Perſon, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was, that ſuffered even for Sinners, and not be moved thereby to grief and compaſſion; and yet poſſibly theſe affections may be no other than ſuch as would be excited from us, at the reading of ſome Tragedy in a Romance or feigned Story.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Affections may be moved by the <hi>Artificial Rhetorick</hi> of others, by the great abilities of the Miniſters whom we hear. God tells the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> Cap. 33.32. <hi>Thou art to them as a very lovely ſong;</hi> they may ſometimes have their judgments pleaſed, with the Learning ſhewn in a Sermon, and their affections excited by the Oratory, and powerful ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance of it; but theſe though they are very good helps to excite our affections, yet they are not true teſts of ſpiritual affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Pride and ſelf-ſeeking may in the performance of duties excite our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49760:24"/>affections. Men may be much deceived in this particular, for inſtance, in Prayer, they may think they are affected with the things they pray for, when poſſibly their affections may be moved only with the words themſelves ſpeak, with the copious, free and admirable inventive way that they pray in: Whereas the contrite broken Spirit, who is only moved with truly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual affections, may not be ſo large, and ſo copious in his expreſſions of them. A true Chriſtian may <hi>groan out a Prayer,</hi> that cannot compoſe and make a Prayer, that hath a ſententious Coherence one part with another. As the Ground that is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of <hi>precious Mines</hi> hath leaſt graſs grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it; ſo ſometimes in holy Duties, when the heart is moſt full of Grace, there may be leaſt flouriſhing of expreſſions: You cannot gather the truth of ſaving Grace, from ſtrong workings of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which may ſometimes upon theſe accounts be deceitful and wicked, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Men may have Affections ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in them upon theſe grounds, but then they are always vaniſhing and fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and are only permanent while the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of ſome external cauſe doth excite them, and they are always unfruitful,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49760:25"/>though their affections may ſtir within them, yet they are not efficacious to put them upon a holy Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <head>SERMON III.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. EVery change that is wrought upon the <hi>Will,</hi> is no certain evidence of the truth of Grace; a Man may fall ſhort of true ſaving Grace, when there is yet a great change wrought upon the Will; it is true, it is the through change of the Will, wherein Grace doth principally conſiſt; this is the firſt principal Act from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life, without which, whatſoever other change is wrought upon us, it is no more than to ſet the hand of the Watch to the right hour when the Spring is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The Philoſophers call the <hi>Will,</hi> the commanding, ſwaying faculty of the Soul, that controuls all the Inferior faculties, and makes them obey its inclinations; ſo that ſuch as the Will is, ſuch is the whole Man: And therefore the Scripture in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49760:25"/>forth the two-fold State of <hi>Men,</hi> doth it by ſhewing the temper of their Wills; unregenerate Men are deſcribed by their willfulneſs, <hi>Ye will not come to me that ye might have Life,</hi> 2 <hi>John</hi> 4. The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are deſcribed by their willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3. <hi>They ſhall be a willing People in the Day of thy Power.</hi> And here I ſhall endeavour two things,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſhew you after what manner the Spirit of God doth work this renewing change upon the Will.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What other change is wrought upon it which falls ſhort of true Grace, though oftentimes it is taken for it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, We muſt know that there are two ways, whereby God doth effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally change the Heart and Will of a Sinner: And theſe are <hi>Moral Swaſions, and Phyſical Determinations,</hi> which is nothing elſe, but God's All powerful Grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth immediately turn the bent and inclination of the Will towards himſelf, and both theſe do always concurr and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to this great change. He doth firſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49760:26"/>convince a Sinner, and perſwade him of the rationality of the ways of God, of the vileneſs and emptineſs of thoſe vain things, which his deſires ſo eagerly purſue: And on the other hand, he clearly repreſents the Glory and Excellency of himſelf and his ways, that he is the greateſt good that we can enjoy; and yet there is no other way to enjoy him, but by loving and ſerving of him: To do this he makes uſe of moral Swaſions, and works upon our reaſon, by cogent and prevailing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which at laſt diffuſeth ſuch Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſweetneſs through the heart of a Chriſtian, which makes him diſreliſh thoſe fulſome delights of ſin, that ſeparate from that infinite Good, with which it holds compariſon, ſo that he finds more true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in God and his ways, and more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring and charming joy in them, than ever he did before in ſenſual pleaſure; more are thereby carryed forth unto them, by an infallible, yet altogether free, voluntary and amorous motion; and this is done by the real efficiency likewiſe of the Spirit of God upon the Will, and this efficiency, is ſo ſweetly attempered to the native Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Will, that it will be a pain and a torment to the Soul, to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49760:26"/>from that God, whom now his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doth apprehend, and whom his Will doth claſp about, as the real and chiefeſt good. Here you ſee are both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Swaſions, and Phyſical Determinations, of the Will to the Work of Grace; God doth really determine it by the efficacious touch of his Grace, whereby he power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully turns the bent and inclination of it to himſelf, which before ſtood towards ſin and vanity; and that this might not infringe the Wills Prerogative of acting freely, he doth at the ſame time morally perſwade it, by repreſenting himſelf as the beſt and moſt ſatisfying object of it; notwithſtanding the irreſiſtableneſs of God's working upon the Will; yet ſtill Man's Will is free in God's working of Grace, which ſome have thought to be an irreconcilable difference.</p>
            <p>For the freedom of the Will doth not conſiſt in redoubled pure Acts, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Saints and Angels themſelves, that are under that bleſſed neceſſity, that they cannot but love and ſerve God, would not love him and ſerve him freely: The liberty of the Will, conſiſts in an acting upon rational grounds and motives, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49760:27"/>by how much ſtronger they are, by ſo much more they turn the neceſſity of the Will to him, and yet by ſo much the more the Will is free in acting: So that here the liberty of the Will may not violate the cauſality of God's purpoſe, he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it by the power of his irreſiſtible Grace. And yet that this irreſiſtible Grace, may not violate the liberty of the Will, which is its natural privilege, he perſwades it by ſuch natural Arguments, that it could not act freely if it ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from them, though God uſeth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power, yet he uſeth no violence, he ſubdues the Will, but doth not compell it. This is that victorious Grace, that doth not more overcome a Sinner's reſiſtance, than it doth his prejudice; it overcomes all oppoſition by its own irreſiſtible Power, and overcomes all its prejudices by its at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive ſweetneſs: And whenever it brings him to ſubmit to God, it makes him to apprehend, that his chiefeſt happineſs and joy is to do ſo. And it is the ſame that doth afterwards preſerve a Chriſtian from total Apoſtacy, for though there be ſuch a conſtant ſupply of Grace to keep them, that they ſhall never draw back to Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet withal, their own freedom is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49760:27"/>ſuch, that they may if they will, but when the Will ceaſeth its freedom, it never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines but to that which is moſt pleaſing, and nothing is pleaſing to a renewed, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Will, ſo much as that <hi>Sovereign good,</hi> which comprehends in it all other good. Thus you ſee, how God diſpoſeth of the <hi>Will</hi> of Man, changing it without conſtraining of it, turning it not forcibly, but infallibly to himſelf, when he draws it by the ſweet and efficacious operation of his Grace; Thus I have diſpatched the firſt thing, and ſhewed how God works the renewing change upon the Will of a Sinner.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular is to ſhew you, what other Change may be wrought upon the Will; which yet falls ſhort of true Grace, and may bring a Man almoſt to Chriſtianity, and yet leave him in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, an unregenerate Man may have many faint velleities, and wiſhings, and wouldings after Grace; when he hears ſo much ſpoken of the <hi>Beauty</hi> and excellency of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> he is convinced in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that thoſe things are true, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49760:28"/>Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee the Lord; and that though while he is carnal, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duties are tedious and a burthen to him; yet were he ſpiritualized, they would become more delightful to him than thoſe very pleaſures of ſin, which keep him from cloſing with Grace: Were he renewed thoſe very pleaſures of ſin would become unſavoury to him, that which now he is afraid to loſe if he would turn to Conſcience he would not value the loſs of it. When an unregenerate Man, I ſay, is thus convinced of this, it will make him to break out into <hi>pangs of Affection</hi> wiſhing for Grace. O that I were holy and gracious! I wiſh my heart were chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and renewed: I wiſh I were better and could do better; I appeal to every Man's Conſcience, when he hath been convinced of the excellency and deſirableneſs of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, whether they have not breathed forth ſuch wiſhes as theſe are. When <hi>you have</hi> ſeen a Chriſtian that is eminent and exemplary for piety; have not you wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſelves in his condition, not only in reſpect of his future reward and glory, but alſo in reſpect of his preſent Grace. Have you not wiſhed that ſuch had been your comelineſs and beauty, have you not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49760:28"/>wiſhed not only with <hi>Balaam,</hi> to <hi>die the death of the righteous,</hi> and that your <hi>laſt end</hi> might be <hi>like his;</hi> but alſo your Life by living righteouſly; and yet ſtill continue in the ſame courſe and ſinful ſtate as formerly? Why now ſuch empty Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leities, and idle Wiſhes an unregenerate man may poſſibly have; he may wiſh he were a Saint, even as a fond fooliſh man, according to his idle fancy, may wiſh that he were an Angel; but ſuch wiſhes do not put them upon a conſtant attempt and uſe of the Means whereby they might become ſuch, their wiſhes and their ſighs vaniſh away together, the one retaining no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger an impreſſion upon their hearts, than the other in the Air; he runs into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of that ſin, which with his mouth he wiſhes he might not commit, and lives in the neglect of holy duties, and yet can wiſh that he had performed them; ſuch contradictory wiſhes have unregenerate men; they wiſh themſelves holy, and yet are wilfully ſinful; they wiſh that they were better, and yet will not endeavour their own amendment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An unregenerate man, he may not reſt in theſe Wiſhes, but he may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49760:29"/>riſe to a <hi>Reſolution;</hi> I ſay, to ſome degree of Reſolution: They reſolve many things; That their Luſts ſhall no longer enſlave them; That the Pleaſures of the World ſhall no longer bewitch them; That the Difficulties of Religion ſhall no longer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright them; but that they will break through all, and act like Men: And ſuch generous and ingenuous Reſolutions as theſe a man in his natural eſtate may forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelf with. Grace they know they muſt have, elſe they are eternally undone; they know that God hath not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their endeavours, and they perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily reſolve that they will not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themſelves. We may ſee the ſame ſtrong reſolutions of thoſe that came to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> chap. 42.5, 6. <hi>They ſaid, the Lord be a true and faithful witneſs between us, if we do not according to all things for which the Lord thy God ſhall ſend thee to us,</hi> &amp;c. And yet none more rebellious and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent againſt God than theſe men that make this Remonſtrance. And now notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Wiſhes, and theſe Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the <hi>Will</hi> of a <hi>Natural Man</hi> falls ſhort of a ſaving Change, and that uſually in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49760:29"/>
            <p>Firſt, In that it is a <hi>fickle</hi> and <hi>unconſtant Will;</hi> their Deſires may be ſometimes vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and paſſionate, as if they would take Heaven by force, and wreſt Mercy out of the hands of God: their Prayers may be importunate and earneſt, as if they would take no denial; but this violent Spirit is ſoon ſpent, and this full Bent of their Souls ſoon flaggs, and returns again, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, ever and anon into the commiſſion of ſome foul and groſs Sins. Such a <hi>Will</hi> as this is, though at firſt it hurries them apace, yet it is ſoon tired, and leaves them ſhort of Grace and Heaven. The Chriſtian Race is not to be run by ſo many fits, but by a conſtant courſe and progreſs, ſtill getting ground upon our Luſts, ſtill approaching nearer to the Kingdom of Heaven: But it is with ſuch men as it is with the Sea when a ſpring-tide covers all the ſhoar; when it ebbs, it diſcovers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Sands, which before was nothing but deep Water; ſo theſe affected and flowing Chriſtians, they diſcover that there is nothing but barren Sands at the bottom, that they are as <hi>unſtable as Water.</hi> A Chriſtian is not made in a Fit, neither is the Work of Grace wrought in a Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but it is a ſetled, ſolemn, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49760:30"/>frame of Heart that brings a man to Chriſt and Salvation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Will</hi> of an unregenerate man is never univerſally changed; ſtill they reſerve to themſelves ſome Luſt or other, that they will not part withall, and their Reſolutions concerning their ſins, are ſuch as the Reſolution of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> 2 Kings 5.18. <hi>In this thing the Lord pardon thy Servant, that when my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter goes into the houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>to worſhip there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I how my ſelf in the houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>&amp;c. The Lord pardon thy Servant in this thing.</hi> So men may be peremptory in their reſolutions to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their Sins, yet ſtill there may be ſome one dear Luſt or other that makes them cry with <hi>Naaman, Lord, pardon thy Servant in this thing.</hi> Now they will be willing to receive Chriſt if they may be allowed in one Darling-Sin; now the partition that any one Sin makes between Chriſt and the Soul, muſt needs hinder the ſoul from <hi>clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Chriſt;</hi> as, if you throw but any little thing between the branch and the ſtock that it is ingrafted into, the Sap will never be communicated to it, and ſo it will never grow up to be a Plant.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49760:30"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The Will of an unregenerate Man is uſually <hi>irrational;</hi> it would obtain the End, and yet not uſe the Means. Grace poſſibly they would have, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring their averſe Wills to cloſe with the performance of thoſe unpleaſing &amp; irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Duties wherein God uſually beſtows Grace, and by which he conveys Grace to the Soul. Could they be holy with a wiſh, and a ſudden fancy that inflames them, then none ſhould be better Chriſtians than themſelves; could they enter into Heaven by being willing, there is none then ſhould ſhine above them in Glory; but when there is ſo much hard and unpleaſing work, firſt that they muſt be born of God, and after they are true Chriſtians they muſt exerciſe every Grace, and perform every Duty that may ſit and prepare them for Glory, they look upon theſe things as too difficult, which makes them ſit down with idle Wiſhes ſhort both of Grace and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; their <hi>Wills</hi> are very <hi>irrational;</hi> they would have Heaven, but they ſlight Grace, the way to it; and poſſibly they would have Grace, but they cannot bring themſelves to the performance of thoſe irkſome and unpleaſing Duties in and by which Grace is uſually beſtowed and conveyed.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49760:31"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The <hi>Will</hi> of an unregenerate Man is uſually general, not a particular Will. If God ſhould ask them, Sinner, what would you do to be ſaved? They would anſwer, Any thing, every thing. But let God bid them leave ſuch and ſuch a Sin, perform ſuch and ſuch a Duty, they anſwer with <hi>Naaman,</hi> Any Sin but that; any Duty but that. So it is with theſe Men; Oh any thing in the general; but when God brings them down to Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to do this or that, then they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do juſt nothing.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewed you how far the Will it ſelf may be changed in unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſons; they may wiſh after Grace, and reſolve to be better, and to do better, and yet fall ſhort of ſaving Grace; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what it is that hinders this change from being a through work of Grace, what it is that obſtructs them when they are <hi>almoſt,</hi> that they are not <hi>altogether Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, As for the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a great change wrought in the Lives of unregenerate perſons
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49760:31"/>who yet fall ſhort of Chriſtianity. The Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. ſpeaks of ſuch who <hi>having eſcaped the pollutions of the world, through Luſt were again entangled therein, and overcome,</hi> &amp;c. It ſeems to eſcape the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the world, is no Argument of true Grace, unleſs they be alſo cleanſed from the pollutions of the Heart; for ſin may be left merely from external and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Principles, ſuch as Terrors of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for the heavy Judgments of God. When God ſets up a flaming ſword between a ſinner and thoſe ſins which he accounts his Paradiſe here; now to leave ſin upon ſuch a ſtrait as this is, is to leave it with a great deal of reluctancy; as when a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner in a ſtorm caſts his goods over-board into the ſea, it is with his will indeed; but it is with an unwilling willingneſs; he is frighted and terrified to it: ſo when the ſoul is toſſed with the Tempeſt of divine wrath, and when ready to be ſplit upon the Rock of Ages, and ſunk and be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in a Sea of Fire and Brimſtone, he is forced to light himſelf, and to caſt this and that dear Luſt over-board; this he doth from his will; but it is ſuch a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced will as that of Mariners, who throw their Treaſure over-board, and as ſoon as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49760:32"/>the Tempeſt is over, the one gathers up his floating wrecks, and the other his ſins. Theſe men leave their ſins as <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wiſe left <hi>Sodom;</hi> they dare no longer continue in it leſt Fire and Brimſtone rain upon them, and yet when they do leave them, they give many a wiſhly look back again, and have ſtrong and vehement deſires after them. That <hi>Reformation of Life</hi> that only frees us from debauchedneſs, that falls far ſhort of true Chriſtianity, and of making us <hi>altogether Chriſtians;</hi> this is that with which many ſooth up themſelves when they they reflect back upon the wild ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagances of their former time, how outrageouſly wicked they have been, rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, drunkards, unclean, blaſphemers, and now they find themſelves deadned to theſe ſins, and grown men of ſtaid and ſober lives, they ſtraightway conclude, Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this great change could never be made on them otherwiſe than by the renewing work of the Holy Ghoſt; and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this amendment there may be no work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation; for men may gather up their looſe and diſſolute Lives within ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of Civility and Morality, and yet be utterly ſtrangers to this Work. Much of this may be aſcribed partly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49760:32"/>of God's Spirit, awakening natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſcience to ſee the horrour and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuch daring and <hi>outrageous</hi> ſins, and partly too from Prudence, gotten from frequent experience of manifold inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that they brought upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſuch ſins; and both theſe Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and moral Prudence are Principles that fall very far ſhort of true Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Uſually all the ſpecious Reformation and Amendment of theſe mens Lives, is in effect either a changing of the Sin, or a tiring out the Sinner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Life</hi> may <hi>ſeem to be reformed,</hi> when men exchange their rude and boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſins for ſuch as are more demure and ſober; from riotous, they grow worldly; from prophane and irreligious, they grow ſuperſtitious and hypocritical; from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, they grow Hereticks; from ſins of Practice, to ſins of Contemplation: They are apt to think, certainly this change muſt needs be the change of their Nature, when indeed it is but the change of their ſins; and uſually it is ſuch a change too, though it render the Life more inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, yet it makes the Soul more incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49760:33"/>
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his 29th. Epiſtle, tells us, That Vices may give place, when Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e or Grace do not take it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Life</hi> may <hi>ſeem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> when men are only <hi>tired out;</hi> when they have out-grown their ſins. There are ſins which are proper and peculiar to ſuch a ſtate and ſeaſon of a man's Life, upon the alteration of which they vaniſh and diſappear: Sins of Youth drop off from declining Age, as misbecoming them. Now this deceives men, when they look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Vanities which they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aken; how deadned are they to thoſe ſinful ways which before they much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in? They conclude certainly this great change muſt needs proceed from true Grace, when they do not leave their ſins ſo much as their ſins leave them, and drop off from them as rotten fruit from a Tree; the faculties of their minds, and members of their bodies, which before were Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſin and unrighteouſneſs, are now become Inſtruments of Morality and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertues; this ſets them not free from the ſervice of ſin, but only reſtrains them from breaking out into notorious and ſcandalous Vices.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49760:33"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>A Civil and harmleſs demeanour</hi> doth not render a man altogether a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; there be many ingenuous ſpirits, who lived blameleſly in the world, their good Natures nearly reſembling Grace; and ſuch was <hi>Paul</hi>'s before his converſion: For he tells us, <hi>As touching the Law, he was blameleſs:</hi> So the young man that came to Chriſt to know what Leſſon he had fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take out. This only argues a ſweet Diſpoſition, but not a gracious Heart. Thus you ſee how diſſolute men may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake themſelves in this Work, upon which their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernal happineſs depends. It is to be ſeared that many may reſt upon theſe, and think the great diſcriminating change to be wrought, only becauſe they are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally honeſt, or gained over to a profeſſion of Truth, or to ſuch a Party or Sect of Profeſſors; when indeed true Chriſtianity conſiſts not in theſe things.</p>
            <p>This ſhall ſuffice for the firſt General propounded; What Change may be wrought upon a man ſo as to bring him almoſt to Chriſtianity, and yet leave him ſhort of being a Chriſtian: I ſhall cloſe up this Branch with ſome <hi>Practical Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49760:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. What then ſhall become of ſuch as fall ſhort of thoſe that fall ſhort of Grace, that arenot ſo much as <hi>Almoſt Chriſtians?</hi> What will become of carnal, looſe, and prophane Sinners? If thoſe that have been gazed at and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired for burning and ſhining Lights, yet have fallen into the blackneſs of darkneſs, even into the Dungeon of eternal dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, were we but ſerious in this Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it would make all our faces gather blackneſs, and fill all our hearts with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, to conſider that we are not gone ſo far in Chriſtianity as thoſe may go, who yet fall ſhort of Heaven. Have we all been <hi>enlightened?</hi> Have we all <hi>taſted of the heavenly gift,</hi> and of <hi>the powers of the world to come?</hi> Have we all been <hi>made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> Are there not many among us poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly whoſe hearts have never yet been tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the ſenſe of ſin, never affected with any of the ways of God, that give themſelves up to all wickedneſs with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, who never have given ſo much as one ſerious wiſh towards Holineſs, when thoſe that ſeemed to ſhine as Stars in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhall be at laſt found burning in Hell; Oh, in what a diſmall caſe ſhall theſe <hi>Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands</hi> be?</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49760:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Hence likewiſe, ſee what a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult thing it is to be a true Chriſtian. May a natural Man attain to all this that I have ſpoken of before? We may then take up that <hi>ſame</hi> Queſtion, which the Diſciples asked Chriſt, (when he had told them, that it was <hi>as caſe for a Camel to go through a needles Eye, as for a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven) Lord, who then ſhall be ſaved?</hi> What, may thoſe whoſe profeſſion hath been eminent, who have been <hi>Sainted</hi> in every Man's <hi>Kalender,</hi> may they at laſt miſcarry and periſh? Who then ſhall be ſaved? If ſuch be not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Chriſtianity ſeems to be rather ſome fanſied notion, than any thing real and attainable. To this we may make the ſame anſwer that Chriſt gave to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>With Men indeed theſe things are impoſſible, but with God all things are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible:</hi> It is impoſſible for Men by their own ſtrength and natural ability to become Chriſtians, but it is poſſible for God to make them Chriſtians; It is poſſible as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> themſelves are poſſible, only poſſible to the Almighty Power of God: There is not any Soul can be perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, but he hath a Miracle wrought upon him, and he himſelf muſt do that,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49760:35"/>which is little leſs than a Miracle, he muſt act beyond the power of nature, and do more than a mere Man can do; therefore well may you ſuſpect your Chriſtianity, who find it ſo eaſie a matter to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Even natural Men find it a difficult task to attain to that height and pitch, where they ſhine in moral vertues, though far ſhort of Heaven, and it is eaſie for you to mount far higher than they, far beyond them; indeed it is an eaſie matter for any to make a ſlight formal profeſſion, to run in a round of Hypocritical Duties, and live a moral civil Life, this is eaſie, there is nothing miraculous in this: But is it caſie to pluck out the right Eye, and to cut off the right Hand? It is not eaſie to cruci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie a darling Luſt, <hi>to cut off the right hand,</hi> when it lifts up it ſelf to plead for mercy, and to be ſpared a little longer, <hi>to pluck out the right eye,</hi> when it drops tears to beg compaſſion, and a little favor to be granted to it? Is it caſie to combate with Principalities and Powers, to baſſle Devils, and deſpiſe the ſcorns and affronts of the whole World? Is it eaſie to live like an Angel? Nay to live like Chriſt, to live like God himſelf? Is this eaſie, when we ſee ſo many tottering Profeſſors aſpiring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49760:35"/>towards Chriſtianity, ſome mounting till they are giddy and brain-ſick with their moſt damnable errors, others tumbling down <hi>from the Precipices of great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may well wonder that any are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when ſuch as theſe miſcarry: Well then, to conſider what it is that is wrought upon you, even that the Omnipotent God hath wrought, (and what it is that is wrought by you,) that that is beyond the Power of Nature: we may well conclude, what a difficult matter it is to become a true and ſerious Chriſtian altogether.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. May natural Men go thus far in Chriſtianity, O be you then perſwaded to go much further! Do not reſt in any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment ſhort of Heaven and Glory. Reſt not in any preſent attainment; and this indeed is the moſt natural Uſe that can be made of this Subject, when you hear how great a progreſs wicked Men may make. I know that the hearts of the beſt Chriſtians are ready to ſuggeſt to them, and they will be apt to conclude againſt themſelves: All that is wrought upon them is but the common work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49760:36"/>therefore their Graces are but Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, and that themſelves yet are ſhort of Chriſtianity; I know that this ſubject may cauſe ſuch jealouſies and ſuſpicions to ariſe in the hearts of ſome; but the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine uſe of this Doctrine is not ſo much to pore upon our preſent condition, as to ſtir you up to make a future progreſs.</p>
            <p>May a natural Man make ſo great a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, as to be <hi>almost</hi> a Chriſtian, then certainly I muſt never reſt any where ſhort of Heaven. Well therefore, the Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11, 12. After he had ſhewn them at large what a height a natural Man may arrive to, he preſſeth them to be earneſt in their endeavours after perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Why, this will be the beſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to you, that you are <hi>indeed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> that you have the truth of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>natural Men</hi> may poſſibly <hi>gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in a glorious Profeſſion, and ſhine like the Sun in its radiant ſplendor; yet like it they have their Zenith, their higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, which when they have climbed to, they fall down again. But a true Chriſtians courſe hath not any declenſion, he may
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49760:36"/>proceed infinitely from one degree of Grace to another, he may aſcend and reach higher and higher till he hath reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heaven, where all his infirmities ſhall be ſwallowed up, and aboliſhed in conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated Glory. And indeed this is the greateſt evidence of the truth of Grace; a natural Man's motion to Heaven, it is <hi>violent</hi> and unnatural, it is forced from him, by ſome external impreſſions upon the Conſcience, Illumination, and common Works of the Holy Ghoſt, which as ſoon as this external force is ſpent, he falls na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally back again to his former courſe of ſin. <hi>As a Stone may be carryed a great height towards Heaven, by an outward vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent impreſſion upon it, but when that force is worn off, it falls naturally back again to the earth. Now a Chriſtian mounts naturally to Heaven, which by reaſon of that dull mixture of</hi> Earth <hi>that is in him, his courſe tends to the Earth again;</hi> But the true Chriſtian ſtill mounts upward from the principle that carries him up, which indeed never totally ſpends it ſelf; therefore if thou wouldſt prove thy ſelf to be not almoſt, but altogether a Chriſtian, continue thy progreſs, ſtill gain ground towards Heaven, reſt not ſatisfied with any preſent
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49760:37"/>attainments, but be ſtill riſing and ſoaring, until thou haſt gotten the World and them too under thy feet.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When you ſee any who have been forward in a Profeſſion, and gone far in Chriſtianity, to forſake their <hi>Station,</hi> and fall back to their former courſe of Profaneneſs: Take heed that you do not reproach, that you do not ſcandalize Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with their Apoſtacy; this is that which opens the mouths and hardens the hearts of wicked Men, when they ſee ſuch Glorious, but yet Temporary Profeſſors to return with the Dog to the Vomit; they indeed firſt bleſs themſelves in their own ways, as being better than the ways of God, as being better than the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion; otherwiſe why ſhould thoſe that ſo long have forſaken them, and with a great deal of pomp, made ſuch a Glorious ſhew and Oſtentation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of Conſcientiouſneſs, why ſhould ſuch return back again to their old ways.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It makes them think, that all Profeſſors are but Hypocrites, that it is but a ſolemn cheat put upon the World, ſince ſuch forward Profeſſors of it are found
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49760:37"/>forſakers of it. Some Men pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a few idle conceits of Grace, and the New-birth Communion with God, and the like unintelligible notions, when there is no other difference between them and others, but what only their fancies make. O take heed therefore, that you do not blaſpheme the ways of God, when you ſee the Apoſtacy of Profeſſors: No, theſe Men were never in thoſe ways. <hi>Had they been Chriſtians in deed, they would never have deſerted thoſe holy ways; their natures were never changed, and it is no wonder, that they are relapſed and fallen back again into their old Cuſtoms; to ſee the Swine that is cleanſed to return back again to the mire, it is nothing ſtrange. Had Chriſt changed the nature of theſe Swine, and made them his Sheep, then as they had firſt</hi> eſcaped <hi>the pollutions of the World, ſo they would have kept themſelves from ever being intangled by them.</hi> But this makes highly for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſtianity, and proves it to be a thing ſo excellent, that it cannot be long counterfeited; Hypocriſie ſhall certainly betray it ſelf by its Apoſtaſie, that it had never any thing of true and ſaving Grace, although it carried far in a ſhew and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of it. Thus much for the firſt thing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49760:38"/>propounded, how far a Man may attain to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſtianity, and yet be in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſinful State.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <head>SERMON IV.</head>
            <p>THE next thing is to ſhew you, whence it is that natural Men are inabled to make ſo great a progreſs towards Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I ſhall give you a brief Reſolution to this Queſtion, and that ſhall be drawn, Firſt, from the conſideration of the Subject, and that is a natural Man himſelf. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, from the conſideration of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and that is Holineſs or Chriſtianity to which it tends. Firſt, if you look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Subject</hi> the <hi>natural Man</hi> himſelf; And ſo you ſhall find that Man, and that which is wrought upon him, which may carry him out poſſibly to a very great progreſs in Religion, and that may be twofold. (1) the <hi>Power of Nature.</hi> (2) <hi>The Elevation</hi> and recruit which that power may receive from a common work of the Holy Ghoſt, much helping nature,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49760:38"/>quickening Conſcience, and reforming the Life.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Carnal Man may be carried very far towards Chriſtianity, from the meer ſtrength and power of Nature; for the mere power of corrupt nature; is of it ſelf ſufficient to raiſe a Man to any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment that is ſhort of true ſaving Grace. A natural Man may ſo prepare and diſpoſe his heart, as that the very next thing to be wrought upon him ſhould be Grace; It may carry him out to the externals of Chriſtianity, and it may be with more pomp and grandure than ſometimes the power of Grace doth carry out a Child of God. When the <hi>Power of Nature</hi> takes on it the form of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> it will make bright and glittering Profeſſors; now theſe externals of Chriſtianity they lie in two things, the <hi>performance of Duties,</hi> and the avoiding of Sin: As for Duties they may ſo far out-ſtrip and out-ſhine a Child of God, in the pomp and gaudineſs of them, as to be their emulation and example. And for ſin there is not any one particular ſin, ſetting aſide thoſe common and unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble infirmities, which are inſeparable from the frailty of humane Nature; but a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49760:39"/>Man may keep himſelf from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of it, by the meer Power of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> And there is ſcarce any ſin, that is branded remarkably in the World, but ſome wicked Man or other doth abſtain from it, and that meerly from the Power of Nature; there are ſome that by this Power abſtain from this Sin, another from that, and a third from another Sin: And each of theſe have Power to abſtain like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from all theſe Sins, becauſe what Power the one hath, it may (poſſibly) be found in the other, ſince in nature there is nothing partial for a Man natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is not ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly again, The Devil when he tempts, he doth not force and conſtrain them; he doth not forcibly move the <hi>black Tongue of the Swearer</hi> to curſe and blaſpheme, nor doth he ſcrue open the Drunkard's mouth by force, to pour down <hi>intemperate Cups,</hi> nor force the <hi>Murderer's hand</hi> to ſheath his Sword in his Brother's Bowels whether he will or no, but he ſollicites the Wills, and inſinuates into the Affections by his Temptations, and make theſe freely move the <hi>Engine</hi> to that which his deſign tends; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49760:39"/>
               <hi>all his Triumphs are but for Beggarly Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories;</hi> he could not prevail over us, did not we prove Traytors to our own Souls? did not we ſurrender up our ſelves, by the conſent of our own Wills? elſe we could never be diſtreſſed, much leſs taken by the violence of the Tempter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As Men may proceed far to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Chriſtianity by the Power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo they may have common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Works of the Holy Ghoſt upon them, that may carry them out to a very great progreſs, they may be made ſaith the Apoſtle, partakers of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. and that is, of its common Gifts and Operations; it is the Spirit of God that inlightens their Underſtandings, that awakens their Conſciences, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites their Affections, it is the Spirit that works Conviction, that works Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yea, and Sanctification, in wicked and unregenerate Men. For we have that expreſſion concerning them: There is a twofold Sanctification, (1) Of the Fleſh, conſiſting in the removal of all carnal and external filthineſs, called by the Apoſtle an <hi>eſcaping of the pollutions</hi> of the World through luſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. And that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49760:40"/>in a ſeparation from all thoſe groſs and vile Sins, wherein the flagitious and debauched World do wallow. (2) There is likewiſe <hi>a Sanctification of the Spirit</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in a ſeparation from a State of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a State of Grace, the one is exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal by Reformation, the other is <hi>internal</hi> by <hi>Renovation;</hi> the former Sanctification a natural Man may be made partaker of by the Holy Ghoſt, ſo as to have his Life and Actions ſtand at a greater diſtance from, and a greater oppoſition to carnal groſs Sins, which the World is generally deſiled with, but this is no more than a common and ordinary Work of the Holy Ghoſt, they may account the blood, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are ſanctified an unholy thing: There is a far different force and energy, that the Holy Spirit puts forth, when it works Converſion, and when it works on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outward Sanctification, in both it may work upon the heart, but in Converſion it works upon the heart ſo as to change it and renew it, but in the reformation of a natural Man, he works upon the heart indeed, but it is only to change and amend the life, the Spirit may perſwade the one to change his heart, but then he changeth the heart of the other: He may perſwade
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49760:40"/>the Will of the one to ſubmit to Chriſt, but then he ſubdues the Will of the other, he perſwades the one to become a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but he makes the other a Chriſtian. Now there is a very wide difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two ways of working, by the one he only excites Men to uſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Power they have, but by the other he gives them the Power they want; And thus you ſee, what there is in Man conſidered, both in nature and with the help of the common Work of the Holy Ghoſt, that may carry him ſo far towards Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is alſo ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the <hi>Object, viz. Religion and Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, whence it is natural Men may make ſo great a progreſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, and that is <hi>twofold,</hi> (1) <hi>The Attractiveneſs of Religion.</hi> (2) The <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviency</hi> of Religion to it ſelf. (1) <hi>The Attractiveneſs</hi> of Religion, and this conſiſts not only in the inward and ſpiritual <hi>beauty of Holineſs,</hi> which theſe Men have not Eyes to diſcern, but alſo in that happineſs which is annexed to Religion and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. This is that which draws out natural Men to all their Attainments, <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs</hi> is the great bait of Men's deſires,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49760:41"/>and that which ſweetens the means tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, though they be in <hi>themſelves</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difficult and burdenſome; yet leading to happineſs they cloſe with it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the apprehenſions of Heaven and Hell work upon a natural Man, more or leſs, forcibly, than the thoughts of the difficulty or tediouſneſs of holy Duties; ſuch is his progreſs, more or leſs, ſtrong and vigorous towards Chriſtianity. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Another thing in Chriſtianity or Religion, that advanceth ſome to ſo great a progreſs, is the <hi>Subſerviency</hi> of Religion to it ſelf. Religion doth mightily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and advance it ſelf. (1) Firſt, in that the performance of one part, and of one duty of Religion, it obligeth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth to the performance of another: As one Sin draws on another, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence likewiſe doth one Duty draw on another. There is a connexion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance between them, <hi>Hearing</hi> enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to <hi>Meditation,</hi> and <hi>Meditation</hi> to <hi>Prayer,</hi> and Prayer for Grace to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after it a glorious Profeſſion, it obligeth to ſomething at leaſt that may be anſwerable to that Profeſſion. Thus one Duty of Religion, it hands a Man over to another, and when he is paſſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49760:41"/>through one, another ſtands ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A little progreſs in Religion it doth facilitate, it is hard at firſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, then having begun to continue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe uſe and cuſtom in any thing makes it eaſie. How! is this ſubſerviency of Religion to it ſelf, that may carry Men very far in it, when they have begun Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and entered upon one Duty, that Duty delivers them over to another, and makes it more facile and eaſie to them, becauſe the precedent Duty as it doth engage him to, ſo it prepares him for the ſubſequent Duty, as well as engage him to the preſent Duty: One Duty doth as it were perform half the task, and bear half the burden of the other. Thus then you ſee, whence it is that natural Men may make ſo great a progreſs towards Chriſtianity, ſo as to be <hi>almoſt Chriſtians,</hi> from the Power of Nature, and from the attractiveneſs of Religion: Now here if you ask me, how ſhall I know, whether it be the Power of nature helped by the common workings of the Spirit, or the Power of ſupernatural Grace, that carries Men out to all their Profeſſion?</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49760:42"/>
            <p>I ſhall give you but this one <hi>diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Character</hi> of it: See whether your abilities be greater in the things that belong to Grace and Holineſs, than they are to natural things. A Child of God who is but of weak parts as to the things of the World, that can ſcarce give you a rational account of ſuch affairs, when propounded to him. Why, bring him but to the things of God, and how admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly will he be able to unfold, even the very <hi>myſteries</hi> that are hid from the wiſe and prudent of the World, but put him upon any common diſcourſe, how broken and incoherent is he, but engage him in <hi>Prayer,</hi> how doth he <hi>expatiate and inlarge,</hi> and what <hi>a Torrent of Divine Rhetorick will he then pour into the Boſom of God;</hi> Is this from nature that he is able to exceed and go beyond himſelf? No certainly; It is very obſervable concerning the ways of God what the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa</hi> 53.8. <hi>A high way ſhall be there, and it ſhall be called a way of holineſs, the unclean ſhall not paſs over it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though they wander and err in every other way, though they do not take the right way to be rich, and great, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49760:42"/>in the World; yet theſe that are fools in every thing elſe they ſhall not err from the way of Holineſs, and therein lies the only Wiſdom. But now take a meer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arnal Man, that hath eminent abilities in earthly things; uſually, he is never weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than when he is engaged in that which is holy and ſpiritual; at leaſt his chiefeſt excellency doth not lie there, though he doth perform the Duty well, yet he doth not do it beyond what he doth in ordinary and natural things. Now how is it with you? Do you find your ſelves carried much beyond the rate and ſize of your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural abilities, that you never ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed your ſelves, nor do ſo well as when you are about ſome holy and ſpiritual em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that you are not ſo artificial in any thing as in holy performances; this is a good ſign, that it is from the Power of Grace, and not only the Power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that carries you forth to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion you make. I take the extraordinary gifts beſtowed upon unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Men in a vaſt diſproportion from their natural abilities, to be long ago ceaſed.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49760:43"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee what inables a natural Man to go ſo far towards Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>The third general propounded, was to ſhew what it is that hinders theſe profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients from making further progreſs, that when they are <hi>Almoſt</hi> what keeps them from being <hi>altogether Chriſtians:</hi> I anſwer to this in general; It is only through a <hi>willfull</hi> and wretched <hi>neglect</hi> of what they might do, that any of them do fall ſhort of Grace here, and Glory hereafter. It is not from our want of Power, but our want of <hi>Will,</hi> or rather indeed our wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs that makes us miſcarry to our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Perdition. I ſhall illuſtrate this by a plain and obvious Similitude: Suppoſe that God ſhould promiſe to beſtow Heaven upon us, if we would but reach forth and touch it with our hands: Now although we can never reach ſo high; yet if we do not ſtretch forth our hands, and reach as high as we are able to do, the fault of loſing Heaven will not lie upon the ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and impoſſibility, that was in us to touch it, but it lies in our <hi>willful neglect</hi> of ſtriving to our utmoſt to do what we are able to do; why, the reaſon why we fall ſhort, would not be becauſe our
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49760:43"/>Arm is not long enough, but becauſe we do not ſtretch it forth to the utmoſt length.</p>
            <p>The inſtance is ſomewhat plain and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, but yet it holds an exact propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the caſe in hand, God promiſeth Heaven to us if we will but touch it, that is, if we will lay hold on Chriſt by Faith, which Faith we can no more work in our ſelves by our own proper efficiency, than touch Heaven with our Finger; yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, if we do not do our utmoſt, our falling ſhort of Heaven and Faith cannot be imputed to the impoſſibility that we lay under, but to our willful ſloth and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. It is not Men's <hi>cannots</hi> but their <hi>will nots,</hi> not their <hi>Impotency</hi> but their <hi>Obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> that deſtroys them; <hi>Ye will not come to me that ye might have life,</hi> John 5.40. <hi>Ye will not.</hi> Doth not Chriſt himſelf tell us, that no Man can come to him, except the Father draw him? True, but the fault lies in the ſtubbornneſs of your <hi>wills;</hi> though you could come, you would not; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not your weakneſs but your willfulneſs, that keeps you from coming to Chriſt. Let me here appeal to your ſelves; Doth not he deſerve Eternal Death,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49760:44"/>who had a Power in his hand to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Chriſtian, and yet would not; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you will all conclude, this Man is very equally and juſtly dealt with, if ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to Eternal Miſery, ſince he had a Power to avoid that miſery, and to lay hold on Eternal Life and Happineſs; his condemnation lies on his own head for his willful contempt of Salvation, which he had a Power to work out, and by a diligent improvement of the means ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to him, to make ſure of it; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carnal Man if he had power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert himſelf, yet through his willful neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and obſtinacy he would not do it; and this appears, becauſe there is not one of us that doth as much as he might do.</p>
            <p>There is not one natural Man that doth as much as he might do: Will not he now do what he can do to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and diſpoſe his heart for Grace, then much leſs would he work Grace in his heart, though he had a Power to do it; and therefore the whole default of Men's falling ſhort of Grace, lies in their willful neglects. Men indulge themſelves in carnal ſloth, and if they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49760:44"/>can but maintain the pace and rate of common ordinary Profeſſors in a formal courſe of Duty, or abſtain from groſs Sins; O then they are contented! and will be drawn on no further. Could not they command their thoughts to dwell more fixedly, and more abidingly upon Spiritual Objects? Cannot they be oftener in Meditation, and meditate more fervently, and with more affection? In both had they not Power to refuſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and ſinful motions? Doth the Devil uſe any force or violence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them? Did they ever find, when they threw themſelves upon their Knees in Prayer, that he ſtiffened them that they could not bend? or that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſtopped their mouths from ſpeaking, or their hearts from thinking? had he a Power to ſtrike Men lame when they ſhould come to the Ordinances, or ſtrike them deaf when they ſhould hear, or Dumb when they ſhould ſpeak, then there were ſome ſhew and colour of reaſon, why Men attended no more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, why they heard no more atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, why they did not ponder more conſiderately, why they prayed ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and heartleſly; did but the Devil
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49760:45"/>compel them to this, the Sinner might have ſome excuſe; but when he muſt wooe their conſent and allowance, and wait their pleaſure and leiſure, it is merely a wretched neglect or willful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they yield to the Commiſſion of any Sin: Can you do all this and more, and yet will you not? Know that if you periſh, it is only your own fault, you your ſelves are the bloody Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of your own Souls. It will be in vain for you to plead, that you had no Power to make your ſelves Chriſtians; why, you never went ſo far as to make a trial, whether you had a Power or no; for a Man not to do the utmoſt that he might do towards Chriſtianity, though he hath no Power to make himſelf a Chriſtian; yet it is the ſame as if he had a Power, and yet will not make uſe of it. O let this that I have ſaid prevail with you, to be not only Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, but altogether Chriſtians, and to put forth all the power and might, and ability, that you have in the working out your own Salvation. Is there not infinite Reaſon, why you ſhould ſpeedily ſet about this important Work, while you have time and opportunity for the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49760:45"/>doing of it? Is it a matter of the greateſt moment in the World, and not to be delayed one moment? Be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded then to the ſpeedy practice of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Some deſperate Wretches may think indeed, that Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men to work out their Salvation, may be of weighty import to inforce the Duty upon thoſe that do expect Salvation; but for my part I pretend not ſo high; let me but enjoy now the Sins which I ſerve, and the pleaſures which I purſue, and for the State of my Soul hereafter, I commend that to the mercy of God, and if I muſt periſh, I will periſh with as much eaſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent as I may. It is hard to alter an irreverſible doom, and if it be to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, it is but folly to hang down the head, and blubber the eyes, and break the heart for that which cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. If I muſt go to Hell I may as ſoon be carried down thither in a flood of tears, as in doing ungodly Actions: Why ſhould I conſpire with God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to make my ſelf miſerable. If he hath ſentenced me to Hell hereafter, I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49760:46"/>may as well ſentence my ſelf to an Heaven here; my future torments are in his Hands, but my preſent delights are in my own; therefore if Salvation and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs be ſuch nice points I forego them, and will embrace my more eaſie and more obvious pleaſures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know no pious heart here, but ſhivers with horrour at ſuch Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, though it be but perſonated; methinks rather it repreſents the Speech of a Devil, who is without all poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Happineſs, than of Men who are in the way to it. Indeed it is the Speech of the Devil, but it is likewiſe in the hearts of Men, when they ſtorm and bluſter at the difficulties of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and narrowneſs of the Way, and ſtraitneſs of the Gate: The Devil inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth this ſuggeſtion, It is as good to periſh with caſe, as to be ſaved with ſo much labour and pains; but what, ſhall we leave Men to ſuch deſperate reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as theſe, and ſuffer them to go dreaming to Hell and Deſtruction? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Religion hath Arguments enough to prevail, even with theſe, if they would but ſhew themſelves to be Men,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49760:46"/>and but ponder how much Reaſon can ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſider, Thou that wilt rather periſh than make thy Life a trouble to thee by Obedience, God may under thy Diſobedience make thy Life a trouble, yea a Hell to thee by his Terrours. Thou thinkeſt that thy Garment of Sin and Pollution, will ſit more looſe and eaſie about thee, than the Garments of Holineſs that are too ſtrait-laced and troubleſome: Yea, but what if God ſhould roll theſe thy filthy Garments in Brimſtone, and fire them about thee? How dreadfully wouldſt thou be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, when inſtead of that eaſe which thou ſeekeſt in the ſervice of Sin, God ſhould make thee thine own Tormentor, and make thy Conſcience an Hell incarnate? Believe it, the wrath of God can fry the marrow in thy Bones, and reduce thy Soul to Aſhes. Read <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 88. and you will think it a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſad deſcription of the State of the Damned. While I ſuffer thy Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours I am diſtracted: And if the Wrath of the Almighty lay thus ſore upon an Holy Man, how fretting and corroding
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49760:47"/>will it be upon the leprous Soul, and upon an ulcerated Conſcience? If it burns up the Green Tree, what will become of the Dry Tree, which is but as prepared fuel for it to prey upon?</p>
            <p>No Man hath his preſent delights and contentments in his own Power, becauſe no Man hath his own Conſcience in his own Power; it will ſpeak, yea, and that terrible things, even then, when a Sinner hath done all he can to fear and ſtupifie it. Conſider again, how is it with you after the rage of your Sinning is over? are you not haunted with fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reflections and ghaſtly thoughts of deſpair and horrour? Could we but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowel a Sinner, we ſhould find thoſe Conſcience-Worms, gnawing and knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about him, and devouring his heart. And are theſe wont to reſolve into trouble, for fear Religion and Holineſs ſhould trouble them? Are they content to buy eaſe and quiet at ſuch a rate, as the loſs of Heaven and Eternal Torments amount to? And is this the eaſe and quiet that they purchaſe with it? The Devil puts a gloſs cheat upon theſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49760:47"/>Men, he changeth not the trouble but the time of it, only they ſhun the work of God, becauſe it is troubleſom in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though it doth leave behind it the bleſſed fruits of Peace, Joy, and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; and they do engage in the Work of the Devil, which as ſoon as the heat and fury of it is a little over, leaves in their ſober thoughts, nothing but Anguiſh, Stings, and Torments; and therefore be not deceived, ſuffer not the Devil any longer to abuſe you, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his drudgery upon you, under the notion of eaſe and quiet: If your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences were once awakened, I know the Work of the Devil muſt needs bring you more vexation, beſides the ſhame, than ever you would have from the work of God; yea, the very omiſſion and neglect of God's Work is a far greater trouble than the performance of it would be; therefore if you look no farther than your preſent Content and Satisfaction, if you would go to your final eſtate the eaſieſt way what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, think not to attain this by giving up your ſelves to a way of Sin, nor by wounding your own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which with trouble afterwards
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49760:48"/>will be ſure to be avenged upon you, but in a way of Duty and laborious work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you only can find preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and ſhall certainly find future Happineſs?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49760:48"/>
            <head>SERMON V.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2.</note> TRue, may ſome ſay, Poſſibly the Work of God might be more pleaſing and ſatisfactory to us than the Work of the Devil, if we could work it; but to what end is it that God requires from us to work, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe doth he command us? Doth not he himſelf know that we have no power? Doth not he himſelf ſay that we are <hi>dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins?</hi> Is it rational, is it juſt to bid a dead Man work? Or doth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that God who would be thought by us to be infinitely gracious and merciful, to mock and deride humane miſery, when he commands thoſe things from us which he knows to be impoſſible? Had he bid us blend Light and Darkneſs together, or to bend the Axle-tree of the World till both Poles meet; had he bid us fling the Stars out of their Orbs, or with our hands ſtop the Sun in the midſt of his courſe; all theſe great impoſſibilities are as eaſily atchiev'd, as by our own power to work any part of divine and acceptable obedience without
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49760:49"/>gracious aſſiſtance from God: We can as ſoon glorifie as ſanctifie our ſelves. What ſhould we then do, but only ſit ſtill and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, till efficacious Grace ſhould move and act us, and we not able to gainſay and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it? till God ſo draw us as that we muſt run, and ſo call us as that we muſt anſwer? till then our Obedience is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, and all our Attempts are vain and fruitleſs. This now is a ſlothful Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's pretence why he will not work; and no doubt but that too often it doth flaſh into the thoughts of moſt men, whereby their hearts are diſcouraged, and their hands weakned in the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Anſwering this, I ſhall not enter into that great Debate of the power of nature to do what is good and acceptable to God; but proceed in a plain and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated way to Practice, and that which will be moſt convictive to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Men will not plead thus in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of far leſs concernment than the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Souls. Would a Maſter, when he commands his Servant to work, take this, think you, for a ſufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49760:49"/>That he hath no power to work till God act and move him? It may as well be objected by your Servants to you, as by you to God. Tell me, what power have I to ſpeak, or you to hear one word, unleſs God do concurr to it? Nay, we are not <hi>ſufficient to think one good thought,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. And do we make this an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to forbear thoſe Actions that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and convenient! Do we therefore reſolve to do nothing, becauſe it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for us to do any thing unleſs God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs with it? What ſtupid, dull Folly were this, and we put it daily and hourly to trial, and produce me that man that can ſay God was wanting to him in his concurrence. What a miſerable and ridiculous task would it be, if in every Action of our Lives that we cannot do without God, yet ſhould ſit ſtill, and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion God's concurrence? Do you ſit down to try whether God will enable you to riſe when you are down? Or, do you que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether God will concurr to another ſtep, though it is impoſſible you ſhould ſtir and move, unleſs God act and move you? yet this hinders not mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: <hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being.</hi> Why do not you do ſo in ſpiritual
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49760:50"/>matters? We can do nothing without God. True; yet put it to the trial, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no God will concurr with you. Certainly that man muſt be nameleſs that can ſay, I was truly willing, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to do any ſpiritual good, but God was wanting to me in his concurrence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe men who thus make <hi>Impotence</hi> a pretence for their Sloth, do not indeed believe what they themſelves pretend. No, it is the inward and ſecret thought of them all, that they have a power to work out their own Salvation, and therefore whether they have or no, ſtill they are inexcuſable, while they think they have this power, yet they ſit ſtill. Although a man be chained faſt down that he cannot go, yet he thinks himſelf at liberty, and notwithſtanding ſits ſtill, you may ſoon tell where the fault lies; it may be imputed for want of Will, and not for want of Power: So here; Wicked men think they have power to work, however they ſpeak otherwiſe; therefore they are utterly inexcuſable if they do not work. It is as clear as the light, that their Sloth proceeds not from their Impotence, but from their own wilfulneſs. I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49760:50"/>by a few Arguments to convince you, that you do indeed think that you have power to work out your own Salvation; therefore if you do it not, you are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inexcuſable, whether you have that power or no.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Did you never, when God hath ſhaken his Rod and Whip over you, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſe and reſolve to work; his Rod, I mean, either of Conviction or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? Have not theſe made you enter into an engagement with God, that you would ſerve and obey him for the future? Did you not really thus reſolve? There are few here, but ſometimes at leaſt in a Fit and Pang of Conſcience have ſo done. And why did you reſolve all this, and yet at the ſame time think and believe you could do nothing? Did you only mock God, and play with your own Conſciences? Certainly your Conſciences then were too much provoked, and too much awakened to be thus jeſted and dallied with. We find this Temper in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they were frighted at the terrible glory from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> Exod. 24.3. See how confidently they promiſe and reſolve. <hi>And all the People anſwered with one voice, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49760:51"/>ſaid, All the Words which the Lord hath ſaid will we do.</hi> So the <hi>Jews</hi> in their great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.6. <hi>Whether it be good, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be evil, we will obey the voice of the Lord our God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that it may be well with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, how many pious Purpoſes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reſolutions have your Dangers, your Fears, and your Sick-Beds been witneſs to? Have they not heard you breath out, <hi>Spare, O Lord, ſpare a little longer; give ſome ſpace; try us yet once more, and O Lord, we will reform, we will amend our ſinful Lives, we will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form neglected Duties, and never more again return to folly?</hi> Are not theſe Reſolutions an evident Conviction? Certainly you thought you had a power ſo to do, and therefore if you do not endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, you are altogether inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Did you never in your whole Lives perform a Duty unto God? Did you never pray? Is there any here ſo deſperately prophane, ſo loſt to all ſhew of goodneſs, that hath not done this? And to what end have you prayed? For what did you perform your Duty? Was it not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49760:51"/>for Salvation? And did you work for Salvation, and yet think you had no power to work for it? It is impoſſible; Mens very Works do plainly ſhew, that they do think that they have a power; ſomething ſtill muſt be done, though it be but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, ſlightly, and coldly; a mere <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> a cuſtomary <hi>Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me;</hi> yet ſomething Conſcience will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire which men reckon upon, and make account to be working out their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Wherefore is it that you truſt unto, and relie upon your good Works, if you think you have no <hi>power</hi> to work out your Salvation? Would it be ſo hard and difficult a matter to take men off from leaning ſo much upon their <hi>Works,</hi> if they did not think that they had power to work out their own Salvation? Men do appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a worth and ſufficiency in what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do in order to Eternity, and bid them forgo their Works, and renounce their own Righteouſneſs, and this is a hard Saying; you may almoſt perſwade them aſſoon to renounce all their hopes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. This is an evident Conviction, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Notions men may entertain to ſtop
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49760:52"/>the mouth of a clamorous Conſcience, when it calls on them for working and labouring, yet they do not believe what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſpeak concerning their Impotence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Did you never when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God was dealing with your Hearts, perſwading you to enter upon a courſe of Duty and Obedience? Did you never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinate, and uſe delays? Did you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtifle the Breathings, nor quench the Motions of the Holy Spirit, by thinking it was time enough to do it hereafter? What need I begin ſo ſoon, or vex my fleſh, or deny my ſelf the Joys and Pleaſures of this Life, even as ſoon as I am come to reliſh them? When Sickneſs, or grey Hairs admoniſh me, and tell me, I am near unto Eternity; when old Age promiſeth me that the Severities of Religion ſhall be no long trouble, then will I look after the Concernments of my Soul; then it will be time enough; then I will repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, obey, and work out that Salvation that will be then haſtening upon me. Tell me truly, Have not theſe been the fooliſh Reaſonings of your Hearts? Have you not thus often promiſed God and your own Conſciences? And doth not this plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49760:52"/>imply, you thought you had power to do it? <hi>Wherefore thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoever thou art:</hi> it is in vain to plead want of Power, God will confute thee by thy very thoughts. Hadſt thou no Power? Although thou hadſt not, yet thou thoughteſt thou hadſt, yet wouldeſt not endeavour to work; therefore thy Ruine is as wilful, and thy Condemnation as juſt as if thou hadſt a power, and wouldſt not work; for thou periſheſt merely thro' the default of thine own Will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Whether wicked men have this power or no to work out their own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhall not now ſtand to enquire; but if they had it, yet they would not work with it; and therefore it is a moſt vain and inſufficient <hi>Plea</hi> to pretend they want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power. Now this appears evidently, becauſe there is no wicked man, that ever did ſo much as he was able to do by the mere ſtrength of Nature, without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of ſupernatural Grace; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not their Inability, but their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sloth that doth deſtroy them. Do but anſwer your own Conſciences, Was there not one Duty more which you could have performed, nor one Temptation, nor one
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49760:53"/>Corruption more which you could have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted? Could not you have prayed, read, or meditated upon heavenly things, then when your Hearts and Thoughts have been vain, worldly, and ſinful, and deviliſh? Might not that Time have been ſpent in holy Converſe, which you trifled away in idle, impertinent Diſcourſe, or in doing nothing, or that which was much worſe than nothing? What force, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint is laid upon you? Can you think? And if you can, Cannot you think of God as well as of the World? as well concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fulfilling God's Will, and working out your Salvation, as fulfilling your Luſts? Can you not ſpeak? And if you can, Can you not ſpeak to God in holy Prayer, and of the things of God in holy Diſcourſe, as well as of your Trades and Bargains, thoſe low and trivial Matters that are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Men, much leſs of Chriſtians? What force is there upon you? Doth the Devil ſcrew open the Drunkard's Mouth, and poure down his exceſſive and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Cups whether he will or no? Doth the Devil violently move the Tongue of the Swearer and Blaſphemer to revile the holy and <hi>reverend</hi> Name of God? Doth he ſtrike men dumb when they ſhould pray,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49760:53"/>or deaf when they ſhould hear, or ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when they ſhould underſtand? Is there any ſuch force or conſtraint laid upon you? May you not avoid the one, and do the other if you your ſelves pleaſe? Yes, you can, but you will not; therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you work out your own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion if you could. Is there any hope that you that will not do the leſs that God requires from you, that you ſhould ever be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to perform the greater? Let your Weakneſs and <hi>Impotence</hi> be what it will, yet your Condemnation will lie upon you ſo long as your Wilfulneſs is much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than your Weakneſs. No, Sinners, your precious and immortal Souls will eternally periſh now for want of Will to ſave them. Pity your ſelves; will you loſe your ſelves for ever only out of Sloth? Will you ſleep your ſelves into Hell, and go drowzily into deſtruction? Shall one end of your Souls lie already burning as a Brand of Hell-fire, and you not put forth a hand to ſnatch it out? Is it more painful to work the Works of God, than it is to periſh for ever under inſupportable Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Therefore do you what you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can, labour and ſweat at Salvation, rather than fail of it: Let this never grate
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49760:54"/>nor fret your Conſciences in Hell, that they lie there burning for ever, merely for your wilfull Neglects.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <head>SERMON VI.</head>
            <p>VVHen a man is gone far towards Chriſtianity, there are ſeveral things that make him neglect a further progreſs: As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, His groundleſs fancying of Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and hard Encounters in the Ways of God. Oh, were it but as eaſie to be holy as ſinful, he were wretched that would refuſe to be a Chriſtian; or were Chriſtianity but one hard pull, or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult pang, that would ſoon be over, there were ſome encouragement for them; but when they have already ſtruggled, and wreſtled, and waited againſt the ſtream, thus far, and yet ſee no end, Duty to be performed upon Duty, and Temptation upon Temptation to be reſiſted, ſtill to be combating with Devils, ſtill to be croſſing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49760:54"/>and vexing of our ſelves, no reſpite, no breathing-time allowed them. This takes off their Wheels, and though they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do this, yet they will rather ſit down quite ſhort of Grace, than run thro' ſuch hardſhips to attain it, and ſo they come up in the mid-way, neither holy, nor prophane; but pleaſe themſelves with a mediocrity, and middle rank of Religion, and dare not go further for fear of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; nor yet they dare not fall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther back for fear of Conſcience; and ſo they lie hovering between Heaven and Hell. Now this is merely from wilfull Sloth. <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.13. <hi>The ſlothful man ſaith there is a Lion in the way, a Lion in the ſtreets.</hi> Here the Wiſe Man brings in a drowſie Sluggard dreaming of dangers and difficulties, to excuſe his Sloth; I dare not ſtir abroad, for there is a Lion in the ſtreets: A likely matter that there ſhould be a Lion in the ſtreets; but yet ſee how this Fancy works with him: Any thing is an excuſe for the Sluggard. In <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>As the door turneth upon the hinges, ſo doth the Slothful upon his Bed.</hi> A Door is often in motion to and fro, but it gains no ground, makes no progreſs, ſtill hangs where it did; ſo it is with ſlothful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49760:55"/>that which they have already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to, is that they move to and fro like a door upon the hinges, ſtill the ſame motion over and over again, no new progreſs, no new attainment, and that merely becauſe they are ſluggiſh and lazy, and fanſie difficulties to themſelves, and ſtrange apparitions in the Ways of God, that make them ſtand at a ſtay where they are, and dare not make one ſtep forward. As it was with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who came to the very Borders of the Land of <hi>Canaan, Numb.</hi> 13.32, 33. When the Searchers had brought reports to them, that <hi>the Land indeed was good and fruitful, but the Walls of the City were built up to heaven,</hi> and that there were <hi>many Giants;</hi> and that they ſhould be <hi>beaten</hi> and <hi>eaten:</hi> They were not ſo much allured with the goodneſs of the Land, as they were deterred by the thoughts of the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and though God himſelf bid them ariſe, and enter, and take poſſeſſion, they would not venture upon ſo hazardous an exerciſe, and ſo difficult an enterprize: So there are many forward Profeſſors who are come to the very Borders of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to the very entrance into the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> who, when they ſee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49760:55"/>what ſtrong holds of Iniquity they muſt caſt down, what Principalities and Powers they muſt fight with, and what gigantick Luſts, as the Sons of <hi>Anak,</hi> they muſt ſubdue and deſtroy, this frights them from attempting any further.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To be <hi>almoſt a Chriſtian,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in it thoſe advantages and thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations, which, were they altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch, they muſt loſe; and therefore this is one Reaſon why ſo many ſtick in the New-birth: Such a one is no Saint, and therefore the men of the World em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him; ſuch an one is no prophane and ſcandalous perſon, and therefore the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God embrace him, and think well of him too; and thus he doth hold a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with both of them; which were he altogether either, one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he muſt break off; and therefore finding the conveniency of this neutral eſtate, he ſtops where he is, ſhort of true Grace. Were he a prophane Wretch, then thoſe that are truly godly would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void his company; or were he truly god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then the World would reject and ſcorn him; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odly eſteem and love him, and from their ready Charity they look upon
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49760:56"/>him to be truly gracious. Thoſe that are true Chriſtians (thinks the almoſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) look upon me as ſuch as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and what need I begin by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Zeal to diſoblige the World? And the wicked and prophane reſpect me too, becauſe I go a little before them (though not quite croſs and contrary to them) and ſo I enjoy the good opinion of both ſorts, which were I fully one or the other, I ſhould hardly attain. This man can (as it were) hold Heaven with one hand, and yet hold the World with the other, not loſe his intereſt in the one, and yet retain his intereſt in the other; he can enjoy the delights and pleaſures of the one, and then hope for the rewards and happineſs of the other. Were we lodged in a Star, then the Earth would appear very ſmall, and almoſt nothing, as the Stars do now to us; ſo were we more above, the Earth would appear either as very ſmall, or as nothing. Thus it is with a Child of God; he ſoars up by the wings of Faith and Love to the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Earth appears very inconſiderable to him; but now an unregenerate man, when he mounts higheſt, yet ſtill will be ſure to keep Earth in his eye; he will not loſe the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49760:56"/>ſight of that; and therefore when he hath got to ſuch a pitch that he is able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſomething of Heaven, and yet not loſe the ſight of Earth, there he hangs in <hi>aquilibrio,</hi> and will be drawn no further; he keeps ſomething of the Earth in his eye, and will not loſe nor diminiſh his ſight or ſhare of it for the Hopes and Joys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Falſe Opinions and Conceits</hi> that they are already Chriſtians, hinder theſe forward Profeſſors from being true Chriſtians. It may be they would be Chriſtians indeed, did they not think they were already ſuch. When men are gone far, then they are apt to think they are got home, and ſo they have taken up their reſt, and will be driven on no further; they think that what they have already gotten, is enough to bear their charges to Heaven, and ſo they grow care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of getting more; they are perſwaded that they are Chriſtians, and that keeps them from being perſwaded to be ſuch. I do not intend to forbid eminent Profeſſors to think they are indeed Chriſtians; but let them look how this perſwaſion works
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49760:57"/>with them: Doth it tend to make them more careleſs, negligent and remiſs? When they have been under Troubles of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for their Sins, then they ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a loſt and undone condition, and had hot and ſcalding apprehenſions of the Wrath of God; then they were laborious to frequent Duties, conſcientious in their walking, and fearful leſt they ſhould ſin; but ſince their Troubles have been worn off, they have entertained better Hopes, and better Opinions of their ſtate. Are they not grown more looſe and more regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? They do not take ſo much pains with their hearts, nor are they ſo ſtrict and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſevere in their Lives; I muſt tell ſuch what the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ch. 5.7, 8. <hi>Ye did run well; who hindered you? This perſwaſion cometh not of him that calleth you.</hi> This perſwaſion that you are Chriſtians, cometh not of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you; poſſibly it would be well with them if they did not think they were ſo. Sirs, if ſo be that thoughts of your being Chriſtians, and in a ſtate of Grace, did encourage you to walk worthy of that holy Calling; if the hopes of your good and holy eſtate, do engage you to purifie
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49760:57"/>your ſelves as God is pure, as they will work if they be right and genuine, then ſtill entertain and cheriſh them; but if they turn to looſneſs, remiſsneſs or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, here ſuſpect them to be the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verweening Conceits and Elevations of a carnal heart, and ſuch as will certainly hinder you of what you thus fondly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine your ſelves to be, hinder you from making further progreſs in the Ways of Chriſtianity, in regard you take up falſe conceits that you are Chriſtians al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another Ground whence it is that forward Profeſſors many times fall ſhort of true Chriſtianity; It may be when they are already gotten far, then, the Devil eſpecially doth all he can to hinder them; when they have gone far towards Grace and Chriſtianity, then he unites all his Force and Subtilty to ſtop them from proceeding further, leſt they get from under his power and juriſdiction; he knows if they once become Chriſtians, they are then almoſt out of his reach; and therefore whatever luſt be in the Soul,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49760:58"/>he will then eſpecially ſtir it up; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſerve of Temptations there be, he will then ſend them upon the Soul: For none are more aſſaulted with Horrours and multiplied Temptations, than thoſe who make a great progreſs towards the Ways of God, and are near to the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of true Chriſtianity; becauſe then the Devil ſuſpects that he ſhall loſe them, and that they are even revolting from him. When they begin to move towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and labour after true Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the Devil ſees that ordinary Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations are not then ſufficient to ſecure them; that thoſe Luſts that before ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered and captivated them at his pleaſure, will not now ſo eaſily prevail; for he finds them too reſolute, too rough, and untra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable to deal with; he begins then to fear to what a Rebellion this may grow, and therefore he ſets upon them with all his power, way-lays them with all Ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, circumvents them with all his Wiles and Stratagems; and though theſe be only Armies and Muſters of Shadows, which a man might break through without any danger, would he but arm himſelf with noble and undaunted Reſolutions; yet
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49760:58"/>with theſe the Devil aſſaults and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines them, and that inceſſantly, and doth at laſt ſtop them in their courſe towards Grace, if not beat them back again to their former courſe of Prophaneneſs. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.24, 25. <hi>When the unclean Spirit is gone out of a Man, he walketh through dry places, ſeeking reſt, and finding none, he ſaith, I will return to mine houſe whence I came out, and when he cometh he findeth it ſwept and garniſhed.</hi> V. 26. <hi>Then goeth he, and taketh ſeven other Spirits more wicked than himſelf, and they enter in and dwell there, and the laſt ſtate of that Man is worſe than the first, i, e.</hi> When men have caſt out unclean, groſs Luſts by an external Sanctification, that the Devil ſeems to be diſlodged, when he ſeeks to return again to his ancient feat and poſſeſſion, he finds the Heart ſwept and garniſhed; ſwept from the filth of common Sins, and garniſhed with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Graces, as its ornaments; ſo that there ſeems no re-admiſſion or re-entrance of this unclean Spirit; and then he goes and takes to himſelf ſeven other Spirits worſe than himſelf, that is, as I conceive, ſtronger Temptations, and more prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Luſts, and by them he enters, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49760:59"/>dwells there, and defiles that clean-ſwept houſe, and not only keeps the Sinner from being better, but, makes his latter end worſe than his beginning.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When Men have gone far to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſtianity, natural Conſcience then leaves them, and ceaſeth to excite and provoke them to a further proficiency. <hi>Conſcience</hi> is the Spur that quickens wicked men to make that progreſs which they make. Now when it hath brought them paſt common Sins to known and common Duties, then it leaves them, and urgeth them no further, and ſo they ſit down far ſhort of true Grace and Chriſtianity, which they endeavoured after. Well then, let me ſay to ſuch men, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> chap. 5.7. <hi>You did run well; who hindred you?</hi> Was it the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Religion, or the ſtrength of Temptation, the Flatteries and Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the World, the Violence and Rage of your own Luſts? But might you not nevertheleſs have armed your ſelves with peremptory Reſolutions? Might you not undauntedly and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly have broke through all theſe? Were
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49760:59"/>you not able when you ſtood ſtill, or when you gave back as frighted and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at theſe things, to make one ſtep, and another ſtep ſtill forwards? Could you not proceed ſtill further, and preſs onwards through all theſe? Yes, you might have gone much further if you would; you might have made a further progreſs, though all Hell had armed it ſelf againſt you; therefore if you periſh, there will be cauſe and reaſon to blame your ſelves; you can only charge your damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on your own wilfull ſloth and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>This may ſuffice for an Anſwer to the Third General; Whence it is that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors that have gone far towards Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, yet fall ſhort of Grace, and of being true Chriſtians: They were too nice to encounter Difficulties; they were apt and forward to think well of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they were too faint-hearted to cope with Temptations, loth to diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the World, and would not proceed further than ſpurred on by a natural Conſcience, and therefore wilfully fell ſhort through their own Sloth and Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49760:60"/>of Grace here, and of Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The laſt General propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was to ſhew you the Folly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Miſcry of thoſe who proceed thus far as to be <hi>Almoſt Chriſtians,</hi> and yet will not be perſwaded to be ſuch <hi>Altogether.</hi> The Apoſtle ſeems to be very paſſionate, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1, 3. <hi>O fooliſh</hi> Galatians, <hi>who hath</hi> bewitched you, <hi>that you ſhould not obey the Truth, before whoſe eyes Jeſus Chriſt hath been evidently ſet forth, crucified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you?</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 3. <hi>Are ye ſo fooliſh, having begun in the Spirit, are ye now made perfect by the Fleſh?</hi> What are you mad? Are you beſotted? Are you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched out of your common Reaſon and Underſtanding; that having begun in the Spirit, and made ſo far progreſs in the Ways and Knowledge of Chriſt, that after all this, you ſhould fall back again to carnal, fleſhly Rudiments? Why, the ſame may I ſay to many: You that are Profeſſors, Why, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched you? Why are you ſo fooliſh, as when you have not only begun, but proceeded far towards Holineſs and true
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49760:60"/>Grace, that yet you ſhould give over and ſit down in a ſtate of Nature and Unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy ſhort of it; Conſider but your folly and miſery in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſider, Is is not extreme folly, madneſs, and miſery, willfully to fall ſhort of that which you have already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much pains to attain? What, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the labour and hardſhips, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties that you have already gone through to obtain Grace, now to ſit down ſhort of it, and loſe all? Will you will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully loſe all your Prayers and all your Tears? all your Convictions and all your Conflicts? Shall all theſe be ſo much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain? Is not this much below the ingenuouſneſs of your Reſolutions in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior matters? Do not you uſe to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your endeavours by ſuch Arguments as theſe, I have ſpent ſo much upon it, I have taken ſo much pains about it, therefore I will ſee the end of it, and go through with it. Do you think much to loſe your labour in any thing but Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but in working out the Salvation of your precious Immortal Souls? What though it be hard and difficult to go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49760:61"/>Conſider, was it not hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to arrive at that which you have already attained unto; and are you ſo fooliſh as to be willing to loſe the fruit and benefit of the difficulties you have already paſt, only for fear of difficulties that are yet to come? If Chriſtianity be not worthy your pains, why did you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver engage in it? And if it be, why do you ſit ſtill? You will be guilty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme folly either in this or that. For you enter upon Chriſtianity without ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down, and reckoning what it will coſt you; Chriſt himſelf there brands you for Fools, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.28, 29. <hi>For which of you intending to build a Tower, ſitteth not down firſt, and counteth the coſt, whether he have ſufficient to finiſh it, leſt haply after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finiſh it, all that behold it begin to mock him, ſaying, This man began to build, and was not able to finiſh it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it was not worth your pains, what a folly was it to attempt it? if you thought it worth all and more, what a folly then was it to flag? And could you before you came ſo nigh to Grace, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49760:61"/>ſo nigh to Glory, could you ſee that beauty, and that deſirableneſs in it at ſo great a diſtance, as to perſwade you to come thus far, and now when you are much nearer, and can ſee much more of its excellency and comelineſs; Dare you now deſpiſe and contemn it? when you have not only the promiſe of God to be your incouragement, but you have alſo given earneſt too for that Profeſſion, and thoſe endeavours, and thoſe Duties which you have already paſſed through, they are all (as it were) the earneſt of your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther progreſs; this earneſt you loſe, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Endeavours, and Duty, and all comes to nothing, if after all you reſt any where ſhort of Grace, you loſe your ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt which you give, if you be but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Chriſtians, and reſt any where ſhort of true Chriſtianity. Well, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme folly is this for Men to diſquiet themſelves in vain, and take ſo much pains to pray and hear, and to keep themſelves from many Sins, and perform many Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and yet becauſe they will do no more, they loſe the Benefit of all this? Why, what is it that you do all this for? Is it not to obtain Grace and Glory? And
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49760:62"/>will you do ſo much for ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent end, and yet willfully fall ſhort of it? You may remain Graceleſs without all this Labour; if you are fully reſolved for Hell, why do you do any thing? to Hell you may go without Praying or Hearing, without ſtriving, or conflicting, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming one Duty, or reſiſting one Sin as you do; if you are reſolved for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, why do you not do more, all your praying, hearing, ſtriving, and wreſtling, they will be loſt and in vain, if you do not hold on, if you do not continue. Well, what a folly is it for you to have gone ſo far, and won every ſtep of Ground by clear force, who have toiled in the ways of Religion, with ſweat and anguiſh, and diſquieting to your Soul, and yet at laſt to loſe and fruſtrate all this pains through your curſed and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſloth and negligence; to give all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and fall willfully ſhort of Grace and Salvation?</p>
            <p>Conſider Secondly, Is it not groſs and inexcuſable folly to deſiſt after ſo far pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, whereas for ought we know, had we but proceeded a little further, we
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49760:62"/>might have obtained that Grace which we fall ſhort of? And how know you, but that upon your further endeavours, God might have beſtowed that Grace you ſtrive for, God is not wanting in this kind; to thoſe who improve the Power of nature which they have, he gives the Power of Grace which they have not; Yet when Men arrive thus far, and come as it were to the very Porch of <hi>Heaven,</hi> what thick and dull folly is it, when there is as it were but a ſtep or two between them and Glory, to break off their Progreſs and ſit down ſhort? What is it more labour to go thoſe few ſteps more you are to proceed to, than thoſe which you have already gone.</p>
            <p>Were you willing and contented to do all that you have already done for that which is but like Grace, and will you not be perſwaded to do a little more for that which is true Grace? It may be God may convert you by the very next Prayer you make, he may convert you by the next Sermon you hear, he may give you true Grace, when you next of all oppoſe any Temptation, or when you next of all
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49760:63"/>ſtruggle againſt any luſt, the very next ſtep you take in his way may carry you to Heaven for ought you know. Now the great probability of this, nay were it only a bare poſſibility, it makes a Man guilty of the greateſt folly, who hath gone thus far towards Holineſs to neglect a further progreſs towards it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly Conſider, What a dangerous and dreadful thing is it, for Men to climb ſo high, and yet to have no holdfaſt to depend upon, no foundation to ſupport them; yet thus it is with every elevated carnal Profeſſor that falls ſhort of Grace; he is like a Man that ſtands upon the ſharp top of a Towering Pinacle, where he hath no other hold-faſt but a handful of Air: But the ſtanding of a Child of God is firm, his feet are fixed upon an immovable Rock, even the Rock of Ages, and God reacheth out his hand from Heaven to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him. It is diſputed by ſome nice Inquiſitors, whether a Man if he were lift up above the Magnitude and attractive <hi>Virtue</hi> of the Earth, he may not ſtand as ſafely and walk in the Air as he doth now upon the Earth. It is true of a Child of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49760:63"/>God, when he hath got beyond the reach of earthly Attractions, he may walk ſafely in that ſublime way which leads to Heaven; but now for wicked Men, that have not got beyond the Malignity of the Earth, it is exceeding dangerous, their earthly Minds and Affections, and their earthly Converſations, will in the end bear them down headlong, unleſs they climb ſtill higher, until they have got be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond theſe terrene Attractions.</p>
            <p>Now would it not make you tremble, to ſee a Man born up in the Air, as the Poets feign of <hi>Icarus,</hi> with waxen Wings that are ſubject to melt and fall off, and betray their charge to certain ruin and perdition. Thus it is with every one that have gone far in Chriſtianity; and is it not you that fly only with waxen Wings, I mean the Power of Nature, and the common Works of the Holy Ghoſt, which may fall off and leave you in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ruin.</p>
            <p>And from hence it follows in the fourth place, that theſe Mountainous Profeſſors, who have attained to an high pitch, yet
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49760:64"/>fall ſhort of Grace, becauſe they want firm footing to aſſure their ſtanding; they uſually either deſperately tumble headlong into the Commiſſion of ſome foul groſs Sins, or elſe they grow brain-ſick, and turn aſide to the maintaining of ſome prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious error; this is uſually the Iſſue of ſuch lofty Profeſſors, as we ſee a Cloud that hath been ſucked up by the Sun, how it hovers a while in the Air, but anon it is wrapp'd and whirl'd about with every Wind, and ſo it is utterly loſt and diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or elſe it falls down again to the Earth in Storms, and is turned only into mire and dirt; Even ſo fares it with many a Profeſſor, he is drawn up out of the Earth, and above the Pollutions of the World, by a common influence of the Holy Spirit, and for a while he hangs and hovers in a lofty Profeſſion, but having no firm Baſis to ſuſtain him, he is either blown up by an empty Cloud, and driven away by every Wind of Doctrine, and loſt amongſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sects and Opinions; or elſe after a while, he falls back again into the filthy converſation and worldly pollutions, that he had eſcaped and ends only in mire and dirt, and this becauſe they have not that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49760:64"/>incorruptible ſeed within them that ſhall never die. Indeed true Grace is of it ſelf Immortal, but it is from that engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that God hath laid upon himſelf to preſerve it in thoſe, who are diligent in the uſe of thoſe means, by which it may be maintained. But now an unregenerate Man is left wholly to his own Power, to preſerve him in that Station in which he ſhines: And if the Angels themſelves and <hi>Adam</hi> fell from their firſt Eſtate, merely through the mutability of their own Will, who had power to continue in it, how much more certainly then will theſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Profeſſors fall from their high pitch, who have leſs Power to inable them to ſtand, and greater Power againſt them to caſt them down: To aggravate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Folly and Apoſtacy of theſe elevated break-neck Profeſſors, ſee that moſt dreadful place, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. <hi>For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs than after they have known it, to turn from the holy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment delivered to them.</hi> Why, is not the Wrath of God certainly to be revealed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe, who know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:49760:65"/>
            <p>It is better never to have known the Goſpel, and never to have gone a ſtep in the ways of God, than afterwards will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to deſert them and apoſtatize from them.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſider, The Fall and Apoſtacy of thoſe who are great and eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, it carries much of malice and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in it, which is the higheſt rank that can be in any Sin. If there be any in the World that commit the unpardonable Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, it muſt be theſe Men. There is indeed a great difference between ſinning willingly and ſinning will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; Profane carnal Men they Sin wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, but none but thoſe who have been forward Profeſſors in the ways of God, and have utterly deſerted thoſe ways; none but thoſe can ſin maliciouſly, and merely becauſe they will provoke and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God by their Sins; Now ſee what the Apoſtle ſaith of ſuch, Heb. 10.26. <hi>For if we ſin willfully, after we have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for ſins, but a certain fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful looking for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judgment and ſiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 6.4, 5, 6. <hi>For it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49760:65"/>for thoſe who were once enlightened, and have tasted of the heavenly Gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the good word of God, and the Powers of the World to come, if they ſhall fall away to renew them again unto repentance,</hi> &amp;c. This is the firſt aggravation of their Sin and Miſery.</p>
            <p>But then Secondly, When elevated and eminent Profeſſors fall away they uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall lower than they were before, when they took their firſt riſe towards Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and true Religion; falling away from a Profeſſion, is like the falling down from a ſteep Precipice, where they can have nothing to ſtop them till they come to the very bottom: And it is obſerved, that none prove more notoriouſly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and more deſperate haters and revilers of the ways of God, than Apoſtate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God doth judicially give them up to commit all manner of Sin with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſee that black <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the fouleſt Sins that can be imagined, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. from 21. to 30. The Apoſtle ſpeaks there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49760:66"/>the Heathens, but the caſe is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with our carnal Profeſſors, who do not like to retain God in their knowledge, therefore, <hi>God gives them over to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate mind to do thoſe things that are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Devil takes poſſeſſion of ſuch Men with ſtronger power and force than ever; (as the unclean ſpirit re-entred with ſeven Spirits worſe than himſelf <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.24.) to ſecure that Soul that hath been ſo likely to revolt from him, and therefore no wonder Chriſt ſaith, <hi>the laſt eſtate of that man is worſe than the firſt.</hi> So that theſe eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors when they fall away they uſually fall lower than they ever were before their firſt riſe and motion towards Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Unregenerate Perſons not only fall low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but they ſeldom return to make a Profeſſion of their deſerted Religion; it is impoſſible to renew ſuch a one to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance again. Now how ſhould theſe ſad and dreadful Conſiderations, make every one of us to do our utmoſt, that we are able to get true and ſaving Grace. If we
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49760:66"/>reſt any where ſhort of it. When the Winds of Temptation tempeſtuouſly beat, and the Floods of Tryal, Affliction, or Perſecution ruſh in upon us, we ſhall fall, becauſe we have no Foundation, but have built merely upon the Sands. If you ſtand not built upon the corner Stone, you will fall of your ſelves, yea, that Stone will fall upon you, and cruſh and grind you to powder. Nay you fall off from a ſteep and ſlippery Precipice, where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to ſtop, nothing to receive you but Sin after Sin, and thus you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound from one wickedneſs to another, till at laſt you be plunged irrecoverably into that Lake, which burns with Fire and Brimſtone: And this is the fourth conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; diſcovering the folly and miſery of thoſe that go far towards Chriſtianity, and yet fall ſhort.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though theſe Profeſſors may hover between Heaven and Earth in their lives, yet they ſhall not hover between <hi>Heaven and Hell</hi> in their Deaths. No, the half Chriſtian ſhall be as infallibly and as certainly caſt into Hell, as thoſe who were altogether wicked. Here it may be thou
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49760:67"/>art neither Godly nor Profane, but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after thou muſt be either ſaved or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. There is none (as the Papiſts Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) that hang between Heaven and Hell. Whoever thou art, thou muſt be either in a State of Nature or of Grace, and accordingly ſhall thy eſtate then be for ever, either a ſtate of Salvation among the Saints, or elſe a ſtate of Damnation with the unregenerate. Though thou art never ſo lofty and ſublime a Profeſſor, yet the ſame Hell that holds the profane, muſt eternally hereafter hold thee too, if through thine own wilfull negligence thou ſtop any where ſhort of true Grace. If the <hi>Almoſt</hi> Chriſtians could by their glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Profeſſion gain a cooler Hell, if they could get (I ſay) but a cooler place in Hell, if their Profeſſion could gain you this, if it could procure you Purgatory for venial Sins, or the moderate puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Papiſts call <hi>Limbus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi> then you had ſome ſhew of Reaſon to reſt where you are, but when the ſame Hell, and the ſame everlaſting Fire muſt be the Portion of theſe, who have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo far (and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhort) as well as the portion of the vileſt Wretch,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49760:67"/>whom they have now as far exceeded in goodneſs, as the holieſt Saint alive exceeds them; it is the very height of folly and madneſs to ſit down any where ſhort of true Grace, unleſs they are fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſit down no where ſhort of Hell.</p>
            <p>6thly. and Laſtly, Conſider, It will be the inſupportable aggravation of theſe Men's juſt and everlaſting condemnation, for them, to lye <hi>grating upon this ſad refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Hell, that once they were near to Heaven, but loſt it through their own wilfull default.</hi> It will he the aggravation, (I ſay) of theſe Men's juſt and everlaſting condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, to make this doleful and furious reflection upon themſelves in Hell, that once they were in a very hopeful State, that they were once near to Heaven, but loſt it through their own wilfull default; O when they ſhall lie in Hell, and from thence give a ſad and ghaſtly look up to the Glory of the Saints in Heaven; O how will it pierce their Souls to think, that they were once near to that bleſſed Eſtate, though now there be an infinite and unpaſſable gulph between them and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49760:68"/>that bleſſed <hi>Inheritance,</hi> which the Saints enjoy in Heaven! <hi>Thus will they reflect upon themſelves, though now there be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable gulph between me and Heaven, yet once there was but a ſtep or two that parted us: Had I mortified but one luſt more, had I oppoſed one temptation more, had I put up but one fervent Prayer more; poſſibly I might now have been in Heaven: But, O my curſed, curſed folly, when I was at the very Gate and Threſhold of Heaven,</hi> that even then I ſhould ſtop, and after the relinquiſhment of my Luſts, and after all my Progreſs in the ways of Holineſs, to return again to the commiſſion of thoſe Sins, in which I had formerly lived, when I had already gone through the hardeſt and moſt difficult part of Religion, then to break off my courſe! What is this but procuring for my ſelf this damnation, which I now ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and muſt ſuffer <hi>for ever?</hi> O that Light, that once I enjoyed how it thickens this everlaſting darkneſs! O thoſe taſts I once had of the Powers of the World to come, and reliſhed ſo much ſweetneſs in, how do they now imbitter this Cup of fury, and trembling that I muſt for ever drink of! O thoſe Heavenly Gifts that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49760:68"/>once I had, do but now increaſe theſe Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh torments, and the ſight of Heaven which I have had, now diſcovers to me what I have loſt; nay, what I have will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thrown away through mine own ſloth and negligence. O how ſtrange is mine Apoſtacy! after I had gone ſo great a way towards Chriſtianity, rather than I would move one ſtep further, I choſe to lie here in this Hell for ever burning and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? Oh what ſad and tormenting thoughts will theſe be! how will they fret and gnaw the Souls of thoſe Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with Eternal anguiſh and inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Torments? Thus you have ſeen in theſe Particulars ſomewhat diſcovered to you of the deſperate folly and madneſs, (and miſery alſo) that Men are guilty of that do proceed ſo far as to be <hi>Almoſt,</hi> and yet will not be perſwaded to be <hi>Altogether Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:49760:69"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Blow at Profaneneſs, taken out of Biſhop</hi> Hopkins<hi>'s Expoſition of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>faneneſs,</hi> is the ſlighting and neglecting of things Holy and Sacred. Whoſoever is guilty of this, let his outward Demeanor in the World, be as ſair, and as plauſible as <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> can adorn it, yet he is a profane Perſon.</p>
            <p>The Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Sacred things, are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>God in his Nature and Eſſence.</hi> Whom we profane when we entertain any blaſphemous or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Thoughts of Him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>God in his Name.</hi> Which we profane, when we raſhly in our trivial Diſcourſes, boult out that great and terrible Name, at which all the Powers of Heaven and Hell tremble. It doth ſadly fore-bode the growing Profaneneſs of the next Age, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>Suffered</hi> to call upon God in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, before they be taught to call on him in their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dly, <hi>God in his Attributes.</hi> Which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when our Affections or Actions are oppoſite or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>e.g.</hi> Our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lineſs</hi> proſaneth his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Our <hi>Deſpondence</hi> proſaneth his <hi>Ommpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Our <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neth his <hi>Ommſcience.</hi> Our <hi>Deſpair</hi> proſaneth his <hi>Mercy.</hi> Our <hi>Preſumption</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Our <hi>ſinſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> proſaneth his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Our <hi>Security</hi> notwithſtanding his Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and our <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulneſs</hi> notwithſtanding his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, do proſane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Truth. Every Sin is a kind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Contempt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>encies of God.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for nothing, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49760:69"/>defieth his Wrath and Juſtice without a Temptation?</p>
            <p>What ſhould tempt the impious Buffoon to deride <hi>Religion?</hi> Traveſt the <hi>Holy Scriptures?</hi> And turn whatſoever is <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Venerable</hi> into Burleſque and Drollery? And,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The Time God hath ſet apart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated for his Service.</hi> Unto the holy obſervance whereof God hath condeſcended to uſe three cogent Arguments; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. His own <hi>Example</hi> in reſting on it. 2. The <hi>liberal portion of Time that He hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us</hi> for the Affairs of this preſent Life. 3. The <hi>Ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eation</hi> of this day unto his immediate Service. [<hi>Vid.</hi> p. 207.] But we profane it, when we do not reſt from the <hi>common works</hi> of our ordinary Callings. And do not diligently and conſcientiouſly attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all God's Ordinances, appointed to be performed on this day. And that whether in <hi>Publick, Private,</hi> or <hi>Secret.</hi> The Day is not done, when the Church diſſolves. <hi>The whole of it is holy to the Lord.</hi> Walks and Viſits are not to be the Evening-Work of the Sabbath; but holy and ſpiritual Conferences. Thoſe who have Families to look after, be beſt employed, in ſeeing them ſpend the vacant time of the Sabbath in Holy Exerciſes; <hi>ſc.</hi> Reading the Scripture, giving an account what Truths they have been taught, joining with them in Praiſes and Prayer unto God. In all of theſe, in their Courſes and Order, till Night calls for Repoſe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>The Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Which we profane, when we neglect, or are remiſs in our attendance upon them.</p>
            <p>Some particular Characters of a profane Perſon here follow.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>He is a profane Perſon that thinks and ſpeaks but ſlighly of Religion.</hi> Religion, our chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Excellency, the Crown of our Beings.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:49760:70"/>
            <p>But have we not many, who <hi>deride Piety,</hi> and <hi>make a ſcoff of Religion?</hi> Who <hi>take up their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by chance,</hi> never examining it; Thinking that any may ſuffice whatever it be; Secretly deſpiſing the holineſs and ſtrictneſs of others; thinking they make more ado to get to Heaven than needs. But indeed, they are not <hi>too preciſe;</hi> but theſe are <hi>too profane,</hi> who contemn Religion as unneceſſary and ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>He is a prafane Perſon who neglects the Publick Worſhip of God, when he hath oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and ability to attend it.</hi> God's ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is in two places, Heaven and the Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>He is a profane Perſon who neglects the performance of religious Duties in private.</hi> Every Houſe ought to be a Temple, dedicated to God. And every Maſter ought to be a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> to offer to God the daily Sacrifice of Prayers and Praiſes. Such <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Families</hi> as thoſe which are without them, <hi>God ranks with Infidels and Heathens, and devotes them to the ſame common Deſtruction.</hi> In the Morning Prayer is <hi>the Key that opens to us the Treaſury of God's Mercies and Bleſſings.</hi> In the Evening, it is <hi>the Key that ſhuts us up ſafe under his Protection and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard.</hi> Excuſes are vain, and cannot take off your Obligation.</p>
            <p>Are you <hi>ignorant?</hi> Many are the helps that God hath provided you. Are you <hi>incumbred with your Worldly Affairs?</hi> The weightier they are, the more need you have to ask Counſel and Direction of God. Are you <hi>baſhful</hi> and <hi>modeſt?</hi> Alas, be aſhamed to ſin, be aſhamed to talk looſly, be aſhamed to neglect thy Duty before thy Family; but be not aſhamed to pray, and do thy Duty. Our Saviour hath told us, <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall be aſhamed of me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my words, in this adulterous and ſinful Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49760:70"/>of him alſo ſhall the Son of Man be aſhamed when he cometh in the Glory of his Father, with the Holy Angels,</hi> Mark 8.38. What will become of them who are aſhamed of their Duty?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>He is a profane Perſon that performs Holy Duties ſlightly and ſuperficially.</hi> Our <hi>whole Hearts</hi> muſt go into our <hi>Holy Duties.</hi> And the ſtrength and vigor of our Spirits muſt diffuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into every part of them, to animate and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them.</p>
            <p>Sacrifices of old, were commanded to be offered up with <hi>Fire.</hi> And <hi>no other Fire</hi> could ſanctifie them but that which ſhot it ſelf down from Heaven. The which was ever after to be kept burning for that uſe. Our Chriſtian Sacrifices of Praiſe and Prayer muſt be offered with <hi>Fire;</hi> and that Fire muſt be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rted down from Heaven. The Celeſtial Flame of Zeal and Love, which comes from Heaven, and hath a natural Tendency to carry up our Hearts and Souls thither. But indeed commonly our Duties are either offered up with <hi>ſtrange, unhallowed Fire;</hi> ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Paſſion of Hatred, Self-love, and Pride: Or elſe they are very <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>heartleſs.</hi> Our Prayers are dull and yawning, and drop over our Lips without any Spirit or Life in them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>He is a proſane Perſon that performs Holy D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties for Worldly Ends and Advantages.</hi> For what greater contempt of God can there be than to make his ſervice truckle under baſe Deſigns? A Hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is the moſt profane Wretch that lives. He entitles the Holy God unto the Wickedneſs he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, and makes God the Patron of his Sin. And the Wound that Religion receives from Hypocrites, is far more dangerous than that which open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> upon it. When he that ſpeaks <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:49760:71"/>this tempts Men to think that all Religion is but Mockery.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>He is a proſane Perſon who makes what God hath ſanctified, common and unhallowed.</hi> And have we not many ſuch proſane Perſons? Many that abuſe the Holy and Reverend Name of God about <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous</hi> Matters? Who make mention of him in their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dle Chat.</hi> but are mute and dumb when any thing ſhould be ſpoke to his Praiſe? There are but two Ends that can warrant and juſtifie the uſe of any of God's Names, Titles, and Attributes. And they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 1. <hi>God's Glory,</hi> and, 2. <hi>The Ediſication of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and others.</hi> God's terrible Name is ſo full of Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Majeſty that it ſhould never be uttered, but where the Diſcourſe is ſerious and weighty. <hi>Thoſe who rend it with Oaths and Blaſphemies, ought to be puniſhed by the Judges.</hi> And, <hi>would to God, Laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> put in ſevere Execution, to cramp the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Wretches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill up their fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>har Tattles, with the Name of GOD and LORD, making them to expreſs ſome <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and fill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Theſe. God will not hold guiltleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He holds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contemned, and will revenge the Diſhonour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they do him by it What! Will you dare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the great Name of God <hi>without conſidering</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it a Name to <hi>be ſported with?</hi> To be toſt to and fro upon every light and vain Tongue? Whenever we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntion it, we ought <hi>to how our hearts in the dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtration</hi> before it; to which all the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heaven and Earth bow down with moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Veneration. Canſt thou in Duty eaſily compoſe thy ſelf to <hi>reverence</hi> the holy and dreadful Name, when thou haſt accuſtomed thy ſelf to name him <hi>without any reſpect</hi> in thy common Diſcourſes? Let
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49760:71"/>me beſeech you, <hi>O Chriſtians,</hi> as you tender his Glory, of which He is jealous, whenſoever you ſpeak of God, or but mention his Name, do it with an holy Awe and Dread of his Divine Majeſty. And you, who are <hi>Masters of Families,</hi> and have Children, beware that you ſtop in them the growing Sin of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning God's Name: To atteſt any thing <hi>by their Faith, or by their Truth,</hi> is a wicked Oath; more impious in effect, than louder ones. The By word <hi>Marry,</hi> is no leſs than ſwearing by the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> It is a notable Device of the Devil to bring fooliſh masked words into common uſe. 1. That they may ſwear who uſe them, though they know it not. And, 2. That by uſing unknown Oaths, they may be brought in time to take up known ones. <hi>Vehement Aſſeverations,</hi> be alſo dangerous beginnings of Oaths. By the cuſtomary uſe of them, we ſhall inſenſibly be tripping upon an Oath. [This, and more, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 163. and up and down on the third Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.] To return, Many profane <hi>God's Sabbaths,</hi> invade impiouſly the Time that be hath ſet apart for himſelf, his own Worſhip and Service. Many <hi>make the Bible their Jeſt-Book;</hi> proſtituting thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which God hath ſanctified to convey to us the knowledge of Himſelf, and of Eternal Life, unto the Laughter and Mirth of their looſe Companions. Thoſe very words which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> inſpired for the <hi>Edification</hi> of the Church, the <hi>Devil</hi> inſpires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe proſane Wretches for their <hi>own Dammation,</hi> and the Damnation of thoſe that have pleaſure in ſuch horrid Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>He is a profane Perſon, who deſpiſeth Spiritual Privileges and E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments.</hi> Upon this very account, the Scripture ſets a black an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Brand upon <hi>Eſau, Left there be any For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>or, or
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49760:72"/>profane Perſon; as</hi> Eſau, <hi>who for one morſel of Meat ſold his Birthright,</hi> Heb. 12.16. They are profane, who vilifie the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in Themſelves and in Others. Who diſhonour God's <hi>Ambaſſadors.</hi> And who deſpiſe his <hi>Children,</hi> whom God ſo highly honours as to adopt them into his Family. <hi>He who deſpiſeth him that is begotten, deſpiſeth him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that begetteth.</hi> Contempt of <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> argues ſecret contempt of the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now lay theſe things to your own Hearts, and bring them home to your own Conſciences, and ſee whether you are in none of theſe particulars guilty of Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>Do none of you <hi>think ſlightly of Religion,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it a politick Deſign, or a needleſs Preciſeneſs?</p>
            <p>Are none of you <hi>negligent in the Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God?</hi> Nor in <hi>Private</hi> and <hi>Family-Duties?</hi> Or, if you perform them, <hi>is it not very careleſly and perfunctorily?</hi> Or, if you ſeem zealous in them, <hi>is not your Zeal excited by ſome Temporal Advantages and Worldly Deſigns?</hi> Do you not <hi>make that Common and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy, which God hath made Holy?</hi> Either, by abuſing his <hi>Name,</hi> polluting his <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> or vilifying his <hi>Word</hi> in your ordinary Raillery?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Do none of you <hi>deſpiſe Spiritual Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and the Perſons who are inveſted with them?</hi> If you do, <hi>how fair ſoever your Lives and Actions</hi> may be; although you may think the <hi>rude debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Sinner</hi> at a vaſt diſtance from your ſelves, and account him the only profane Perſon; yet certainly <hi>this black ſtile belongs as properly to you.</hi> And you are proſane Violaters of the Firſt Commandment; Which requires you to take the Lord for your God, and accordingly to honour and reverence Him, and whatſoever appertains unto Him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
